{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This instrument's Pleyel models were preferred by its greatest twentieth-century player, Wanda Landowska. The \"art\" of playing this instrument was discussed by François Couperin, and Domenico Scarlatti wrote extensively for it. For 10 points, name this instrument for which J.S. Bach frequently composed, which plucks strings instead of striking them like the later piano.",
      "answer": "harpsichord NHBB B 2014-2015"
    },
    {
      "question": "A city in this state was praised for \"sewer socialism.\" This state is home to a university whose influence on government became this state's namesake \"idea.\" In 1924, over sixteen percent of American voters supported this state's Senator, the Progressive Presidential nominee Robert La Follette. For 10 points, name this state where Scott Walker was reelected in 2014 to the governor’s office in Madison.",
      "answer": "Wisconsin"
    },
    {
      "question": "This king ended the Ingrian War with Russia by signing the Stolbovo. This member of the Vasa dynasty was succeeded on the throne by his daughter Christina. Known as the Lion of the North, this king was instrumental in the Protestant victory at Brietenfield before dying three years later at the Battle of Lutzen. For 10 points, name this Swedish king during the Thirty Years War.",
      "answer": "Gustavus Adolphus NHBB B 2014-2015"
    },
    {
      "question": "This law's enforceability was upheld in the Supreme Court case of Ableman v. Booth, which invalided the \"personal liberty laws\" many states passed to undermine it. This law led to a contentious trial in Boston over Anthony Burns. For 10 points, name this portion of the Compromise of 1850 which required northern free states to help recapture escaped slaves.",
      "answer": "Fugitive Slave Act NHBB B 2014-2015"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man advocated the \"full dinner pail\" in his second \"front porch campaign\" under the management of Mark Hanna. This man was advised not to go to the Temple of Music at the Pan- American Exposition in Buffalo, where he was fatally shot by Leon Czolgosz (CHOLE-gosh). For 10 points, name this President whose death was followed by the rise of Theodore Roosevelt.",
      "answer": "William McKinley NHBB B 2014-2015"
    },
    {
      "question": "In the 2000s, this institution underwent a controversy when its president, former Treasury Secretary Lawrence Summers, was accused of making disparaging remarks about women's intelligence. This institution, whose early presidents included Increase Mather, is now led by Civil War historian Drew Gilpin Faust. For 10 points, name this university in Massachussetts.",
      "answer": "Harvard University"
    },
    {
      "question": "Albania and Kosovo are the only European countries where a majority practices this religion. The Danish Jyllands-Posten caused an uproar in 2005 when it printed cartoons critical of an important figure in this religion. A 2009 Swiss referendum banned the construction of its minarets. For 10 points, name this religion whose followers read the Koran.",
      "answer": "Islam NHBB B 2014-2015"
    },
    {
      "question": "With David Scott, this man docked with an Agena vehicle, making Gemini 8 the first docking of two orbiting spacecraft. This man, a retired U.S. Navy pilot upon becoming an astronaut, died in 2012. As the Command Module Columbia was piloted by Michael Collins, this man flew with Buzz Aldrin and took “one small step for a man”. For ten points, name this commander of the Apollo 11 mission, the first man to walk on the Moon.",
      "answer": "Neil Armstrong"
    },
    {
      "question": "This country was the birthplace of the starting shortstop and first baseman for the 2015 Chicago White Sox, Alexei Ramirez and Jose Abreu. The names of players like Yunel Escobar and Yoenis Cespedes, begin with “Y,” as inspired by this country’s former ties with diplomats like Yuri Pavlov. For ten points, name this country from which Aroldis Chapman and Yasiel Puig defected, leaving behind the only Communist government in Latin America.",
      "answer": "Cuba"
    },
    {
      "question": "One action in this city led to the escalation of Operation Chammal. Twelve people, including Cabu and Charb, were killed in a January 2015 office shooting in this city. The Eagles of Death Metal were interrupted during a performance in this city, though a “double-tap” incident was avoided at a friendly soccer match attended by Franccois Hollande. The Bataclan theater was attacked in, for ten points, what city, the site of the January 2015 Charlie Hebdo shooting and a November 13th attack claimed by ISIS?",
      "answer": "Paris"
    },
    {
      "question": "This leader ordered the genocidal Operation Anfal, carried out by Ali Hassan al-Majid; that operation included an attack on Halabja, where thousands of Kurdish people were killed by poison gas. This man was captured near Tikrit in a “spider hole” nine months after the U.S. invaded his country in 2003. For ten points, name this Ba’ath Party leader, the former dictator of Iraq.",
      "answer": "Saddam Hussein"
    },
    {
      "question": "This city’s police operates a “black site” at Homan Square, where lawyers are not allowed to speak with clients. In October 2014, Jason Van Dyke, a member of this city’s police, shot Laquan McDonald 16 times; in November 2015, Van Dyke was charged with murder in Cook County. For ten points, name this Midwestern city where video of the McDonald shooting was released against the wishes of its mayor Rahm Emanuel.",
      "answer": "Chicago"
    },
    {
      "question": "This commodity is mined from sulfide ore in the Escondida near Antofagasta. A mine for this metal and gold in Copiap´o collapsed in 2010, trapping 33 miners for over two months. The Atacama Desert is rich in this metal, making Chile the world’s leader in its production. For ten points, name this conductive metal which alloys with tin to make bronze.",
      "answer": "copper"
    },
    {
      "question": "A 2003 dig at this location discovered the possible grave of Bartholomew Gosnold, the founder of this location’s Charter Company. The “Rude Answer” was given by a leader of this colony, who was reinforced by Christopher Newport. It was burned down after a rebellion against William Berkeley, Bacon’s Rebellion, and it was settled by a man who had his life apocryphally saved by Pocahontas. For ten points, name this first permanent English settlement in the U.S., led by John Smith.",
      "answer": "Jamestown"
    },
    {
      "question": "The world’s first openly lesbian prime minister was elected in this country, which saw the Kitchenware Revolution after all three of its largest banks collapsed in the aftermath of the 2008 financial crisis. This nation’s Althing is the world’s oldest existing parliamentary institution. Massive air travel disruptions across Europe resulted from the 2010 eruption of the Eyjafjallajokull [EYE-a-fyat-la-yo-kutl] volcano in this country. For ten points, name this Scandinavian island nation whose capital is Reykjavik.",
      "answer": "Iceland"
    },
    {
      "question": "This country’s current President led a 1983 coup against Shehu Shagari. Abubakar Shekau leads a terrorist organization based in this country, which in 2014 attacked a school in Chibok, abducting 276 girls. Muhammad Buhari replaced Goodluck Jonathan as this country’s President in 2015. For ten points, name this African country where, in 2011, Boko Haram bombed a UN compound in Abuja.",
      "answer": "Nigeria"
    },
    {
      "question": "During one campaign, this man’s running mate asked “Who am I? Why am I here?” in a debate’s opening statement. During that campaign, this man claimed that a “giant sucking sound” could be heard as NAFTA funneled jobs to Mexico. This founder of Electronic Data Systems spent $60 million on his campaign, but finished third behind George H.W. Bush and Bill Clinton. For ten points, name this Texan billionaire who ran as an independent in the 1992 Presidential election.",
      "answer": "Henry Ross Perot"
    },
    {
      "question": "Conspiracy theories about this organization have emerged after the shooting death of Seth Rich in Bloomingdale.DonnaBrazilebecametheinterimleaderofthisorganizationaftertheresignationofDebbie Wasserman-Schulz. Russia may have orchestrated a July 2016 e-mail leak showing this organization’s bias against one of its members, Bernie Sanders. For ten points, name this governing body of the political party that includes Hillary Clinton and Barack Obama.",
      "answer": "Democratic National Committee"
    },
    {
      "question": "This physicist worked with the mathematician Roger Penrose on singularity theory. This man names a type of radiation that occurs due to pair production near the event horizon of a black hole. This Lucasian Professor of Mathematics at Cambridge from 1979 to 2009 was the subject of the 2014 film The Theory of Everything. For ten points, name this British physicist, an expert in black holes and the author of A Brief History of Time.",
      "answer": "Stephen Hawking"
    },
    {
      "question": "Giovanni Schiaparelli published a map of this body that included “canali.” The Viking probes of the 1970s explored this planet, whose equator contains the Tharsis Montes. Ray Bradbury names the landing point for the Curiosity Rover on this planet. In September 2016, SpaceX released promotional videos for its plan to send humans to, for ten points, what “red” planet, the fourth from the Sun?",
      "answer": "Mars"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man co-sponsored a bill with John McCain that led to the establishment of USAspending.gov. This man wrote an essay in Glamour for his 55th birthday describing the reasons why he became a feminist. This man’s first signed bill into law was The Lilly Ledbetter Fair Pay Act. This politician’s two Portuguese Water Dogs are named Bo and Sunny. For ten points, name this politician, the first African-American Editor-in-Chief of the Harvard Law Review, who defeated Mitt Romney for re-election in 2012.",
      "answer": "Barack Obama"
    },
    {
      "question": "An attack on this country’s broadcasting company, the RTS, took place during the Bulldozer Revolution in 2000. One of its leaders ordered the assassination of Ivan Stambolic and was targeted by a 1999 NATO bombing. Kosovo’s independence from this state has not yet formally been recognized by much of the world. Slobodan Milosevic once ruled, for ten points, what former Yugoslavian republic that lost its access to the sea after the 2006 secession of Montenegro but maintains its capital at Belgrade?",
      "answer": "Republic of Serbia"
    },
    {
      "question": "For their opposition to one of these laws in 2011, Kansas Secretary of State Kris Kobach called the ACLU “communists” in 2016. A Loyola law study found 31 cases “out of a billion” where these laws would have applied. In July 2016, one of these laws in North Carolina was struck down because it was targeting African-Americans with “surgical precision.” For ten points, name these laws that aim to prevent fraudulent behavior at the voting booth.",
      "answer": [
        "voter ID laws",
        "descriptions of laws that require voters to provide any type of personal identification"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In 2006, an athlete in this sport professed the “whiskey defense” to explain his positive urine test, which was made public four days after he beat Oscar Pereiro to win this sport’s premiere event. Another athlete in this sport founded the Livestrong Foundation after surviving testicular cancer and won this sport’s annual three-week-long race through Western Europe seven times. Floyd Landis and Lance Armstrong disgraced, for ten points, what sport’s Tour de France road race?",
      "answer": [
        "bicycle racing",
        "word forms"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "As part of this man’s business partnership with Bruce Sherman, he serves as CEO and oversees operations despite owning less than 5 percent of his team; as a result, he has received criticism for trading Marcell Ozuna and Giancarlo Stanton in the most recent Miami Marlins firesale. This man, who finished his playing career with the sixth most hits in history, became known as “Mr. November” for a clutch home run in 2001. For ten points, name this legendary shortstop for the New York Yankees who retired in 2014.",
      "answer": "Derek Jeter"
    },
    {
      "question": "After dropping out of Reed College, this man audited a calligraphy class that inspired the “multiple typefaces” of one of his products. A Walter Isaacson biography of this man inspired a 2015 film in which Seth Rogen plays a colleague of this man, Steve Wozniak. After this man was kicked off the Lisa project, he led the Macintosh project until resigning from the company he co-founded in 1976. For ten points, name this business icon and longtime CEO of Apple.",
      "answer": "Steve Jobs"
    },
    {
      "question": "A building designed by this man, Wardenclyffe, was the focus of a 2012 preservation effort led by the webcomic The Oatmeal. David Bowie portrayed this real-life person in the 2006 film The Prestige. This man’s development of a system licensed by George Westinghouse led to a vicious conflict with Thomas Edison, who championed a competing system involving direct current. For ten points, name this Serbian-American scientist and inventor who names a coil that produces AC electricity.",
      "answer": "Nikola Tesla"
    },
    {
      "question": "A former Speaker of this state’s House of Representatives ran for the Senate in 2010, beating Kendrick Meek and Charlie Crist. A Congresswoman from this state resigned as DNC chair after a scandal involving Wikileaks and her hacked emails. Rick Scott governs, for ten points, what swing state that was represented by Debbie Wasserman Schultz in the House and is currently represented in the Senate by Marco Rubio?",
      "answer": "Florida"
    },
    {
      "question": "A myth relates how this location was created after a king performed a thousand years of penance to break a curse on 60,000 brothers who had been incinerated. Millions of people journeyed to this location in February 2013 as part of a Kumbh Mela pilgrimage whose final destination was in Allahabad. Waters in this location are said to have purifying powers because they have touched Vishnu’s feet. For ten points, name this sacred river of Hinduism.",
      "answer": [
        "Ganges River",
        "Ganga",
        "Allahabad before read"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This leader was embroiled in scandal after his wife was linked to a super-nationalistic kindergarten. This man proposed a new holiday, Restoration of Sovereignty Day, first celebrated in 2013. This leader planned an increase in the consumption tax as part of the Three Arrows, his signature economic plan. This leader rules in partnership with the Komeito Party and succeeded Junichiro Koizumi in his current post. For ten points name this current prime minister of Japan.",
      "answer": "Shinzo Abe , but be lenient"
    },
    {
      "question": "Frank DiPascali worked for 33 years under this man, who Genevievette Walker-Lightfoot attempted to investigate. Jeffry Picower was the largest beneficiary from this man’s core business, which led Picower to hand over $7.2 billion gained from it. This man was arrested after he told his son Mark that his business was “one big lie,” and he was sentenced to 150 years in prison in 2009. The New York Mets were among the victims of, for ten points, what fraudster who operated the largest Ponzi scheme in U.S. history?",
      "answer": "Bernard Lawrence “Bernie” Madoff"
    },
    {
      "question": "Much of this state’s La Loma Park was damaged in a 1923 event that began in Wildcat Canyon. A 1990 disaster began in this state’s Santa Ynez Mountains. A Maxine Hong Kingston book details the effects of a 1991 firestorm that killed at least 25 people in this state. The Santa Ana winds have contributed to many natural disasters in this state, including the 1970 Laguna Fire in its south. For ten points, name this state where at least 80 people died in the 2018 Camp Fire.",
      "answer": "California"
    },
    {
      "question": "This group killed thousands of people in the Sinjar Massacre, which targeted Yazidis in the region of Nineveh. On October 27, 2019, the leader of this group committed suicide after being cornered in the Idlib province of Syria; he was replaced by Abu Ibrahim al-Hashimi, whose precise identity is still unconfirmed. Abu Bakr al-Baghdadi led, for ten points, what Wahhabist terrorist group that, at its height in 2015, controlled parts of Syria and Iraq?",
      "answer": [
        "ISIS or ISIL",
        "Islamic State of Iraq and Syria",
        "Islamic State of Iraq and the Levant",
        "Daesh"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The losing running mate in this election year ran for President again four years later despite the National Enquirer exposing his affair with Rielle Hunter. This election year’s “October surprise” may have been a videotape of Osama bin Laden taunting one candidate as “easy for us to provoke.” The Swift Boat Veterans for Truth released attack ads in, for ten points, what election year in which John Kerry lost to the re-election campaign of George W. Bush?",
      "answer": "U.S. Presidential election of 2004"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man, who gave the controversial Gazimestan speech, came to power after the “Rallies of Truth,” where his supporters launched the “anti-bureaucratic revolution.” This man’s downfall began when a wheel-loader rammed a government building, giving the Bulldozer Revolution its name. In part because he failed to restrain the actions of commander Ratko Mladic, this man was indicted at the Hague, but he died of heart disease in 2006 before he could be tried. For ten points, name this president of Serbia during the Balkan Wars.",
      "answer": "Slobodan Milosevic"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man was lampooned as an “anti-poverty czar” by Jack Anderson while Director of the Office of Economic Opportunity under Nixon. This man replaced James Schlesinger after the Halloween Massacre, becoming the youngest Secretary of Defense in U.S. history. This man’s visit with Saddam Hussein during the Reagan administration came under scrutiny during his later second term as Defense Secretary, when he oversaw the Abu Ghraib prison complex. For ten points, name this Secretary of Defense under George W. Bush who oversaw the wars in Afghanistan and Iraq.",
      "answer": "Donald Rumsfeld"
    },
    {
      "question": "This peninsula is connected to the mainland by the Bourne and Sagamore bridges, spanning this peninsula’s namesake canal. In 1902, Guglielmo Marconi made the first transatlantic wireless transmission from Wellfleet, on this peninsula. Located in Barnstable County, this peninsula hosts a family compound in Hyannis Port, which John F. Kennedy used as his so-called “Summer White House.” For ten points, name this Massachusetts peninsula adjacent to Martha’s Vineyard and Nantucket.",
      "answer": "Cape Cod 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Round 2"
    },
    {
      "question": "A song about this movement compares its semi-fictional founder to Robin Hood, saying the founder is “now the Hero of Nottinghamshire.” A group of these people ambushed mill owner William Horsfall, leading to a well-covered 19th century news story about the following trial and execution at York Castle. England criminalized one of this political entity’s main tactics via the “Frame Breaking Act” in 1812. For ten points, name this group of specialized textile workers whose name is synonymous with any person resistant to technological change.",
      "answer": "Luddites 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Round 4"
    },
    {
      "question": "Actor Max von Sydow plays a medieval knight during this historical event who plays chess with Death in the Ingmar Bergman film, The Seventh Seal. Fiammetta tells a story of the king’s inability to seduce a woman while on her first day of quarantine during this event. Ten men and women escaping this historical event tell 100 stories while hiding in a villa outside Florence in Boccaccio’s The Decameron. For ten points, name this pandemic which killed one-third of Europe's population in the 14th century.",
      "answer": [
        "The Black Death",
        "Bubonic Plague",
        "Black Plague",
        "Great Mortality",
        "the Pestilence 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Round 5"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Julio Cervera Baviera developed this technology in Spain, and Reginald Fessenden developed some of its early practical uses. In \"Surely You're Joking, Mr. Feynman,” the young Feynman fixes these items in a hotel. Zenith sold these items, whose first commercial use was by KDKA in Pittsburgh. These items used vacuum tubes or worked in crystal sets, and the first of these items was created by Guglielmo Marconi after research on electromagnetic waves by Heinrich Hertz. For ten points, name this communications technology.",
      "answer": "Radio 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Round 5"
    },
    {
      "question": "Celeste Caiero’s [[see-LESH-tee kuh-EYE-rohs]] actions during this event led to its popular name. A bridge spanning the Tagus [[TAY-gus]] River is named after the 25th of April, the date on which this event took place. This event began after Paulo de Carvalho’s song written for Eurovision was played on a Lisbon radio station. For ten points, name this 1974 bloodless coup in which the Estado Novo was overthrown in Portugal, named for the flowers placed in soldiers’ rifles after its success.",
      "answer": [
        "Carnation Revolution",
        "25 April Revolution until mentioned,",
        "synonyms for “Rebellion” such as “Revolution” 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Playoff Round 1"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The first woman to win this award earned a PhD in political science from UCLA but won this award by demonstrating successful management of common property. That woman, Elinor Ostrom, was later joined by the only other woman to win this prize, Esther Dufflo, who, along with her husband, won in 2019 for their experimental approach to alleviating global poverty. Ragnar Frisch and Jan Tinbergen were the first recipients of, for ten points, what prestigious global award in the field of social science?",
      "answer": [
        "Nobel Memorial Prize in Economic Sciences or Sveriges Riksbank Prize in Economic Sciences in Memory of Alfred Nobel,",
        "Economics in place of Economic Sciences"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "During this war, over 350 tribal forces were killed when Lord Chelmsford led his forces into Natal Province at the Battle of Rorke’s Drift. This war began when King Cetshwayo rejected an ultimatum from the High Commissioner, Sir Henry Bartle Frere, in 1879. This war is known for several particularly bloody battles, including a decisive British loss against a technologically inferior foe at the Battle of Isandlwana. For ten points, name this war that took place in modern-day South Africa.",
      "answer": "Anglo-Zulu War 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Playoff Round 2"
    },
    {
      "question": "The man who led these events faced a personal excommunication from Pope Alexander VI and ultimately execution after a thorough investigation from Sebastian Maggi [[MAH-jee]]. The “Weepers” were supporters of these mass gatherings, and the artist Sandro Botticelli supposedly contributed many of his own works, particularly those including nudity, to these events. For ten points, name these events that culminated on February 7, 1497 when followers of Savonarola burned thousands of “sinful” objects.",
      "answer": "Bonfire of the Vanities 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Playoff Round 2"
    },
    {
      "question": "This disease disproportionately affected males, and had notably high death rates in young adults. It is not polio, but some of the notable survivors of this illness were Walt Disney, Mahatma Gandhi, and Franklin Delano Roosevelt. Camp Devens in central Massachusetts was the site of the deaths of over 800 soldiers from this illness, and, along with the Boston Navy Yard, was responsible for spreading this pandemic’s second wave. For ten points, name this deadly global pandemic, which started during World War One.",
      "answer": "Spanish Flu or 1918 Influenza Pandemic 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Playoff Round 3"
    },
    {
      "question": "Princeton Psychology professor and eugenicist Carl Brigham helped design this product. James Conant and Henry Chauncey found “promising and talented individuals” using this product which was originally designed to create a \"racial caste system\" for race purity. In 2019, an \"Adversity Score\" based on factors like level of crime in a student's neighborhood was added to this exam. For ten points, name this College Board and ETS- developed college admissions exam, a competitor of the ACT.",
      "answer": [
        "Scholastic Aptitude Test",
        "SAT",
        "or Scholastic Assessment Test",
        "or SAT I: Reasoning Test"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A holder of this position became the highest-ranking U.S. official to visit Antarctica in 2016, staying overnight at McMurdo Station. One of these people claimed the U.S. went to Afghanistan to \"deal with the folks who attacked us on 9/11 and we have succeeded in that mission\" in response to comparisons of the fall of Kabul with the capture of Saigon. Antony Blinken and John Kerry are recent Democrats to hold this office. For ten points, name this position, the primary foreign minister of the United States.",
      "answer": [
        "Secretary of State",
        "State Secretary"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1980, this man sent a large number of criminals and mental patients among a group of dissidents allowed to leave his country in the Mariel boatlift. In 1961, the Democratic Revolutionary Front launched a disastrous attempt to overthrow this man known as the \"Bay of Pigs\" invasion. Two years earlier, this man took power after deposing Fulgencio Batista [[ful-JEN-syoh bah-TEE-stah]] with the aid of Che Guevara [[cheh geh- VAH-rah]]. For ten points, name this revolutionary who was the dictator of communist Cuba from 1959 to 2008.",
      "answer": "Fidel Castro or Fidel Alejandro Castro Ruz"
    },
    {
      "question": "Judy Clarke has been nicknamed “St. Jude” for her work in preventing this practice. Furman v. Georgia put a moratorium on this practice until the states could demonstrate they were no longer arbitrary or discriminatory in how this practice was done. Atkins v. Virginia ruled that the intellectually disabled could not undergo this punitive practice, which was applied to the Rosenbergs and Timothy McVeigh. For ten points, name this practice that was often accomplished with the electric chair.",
      "answer": [
        "Capital Punishment [",
        "the Death Penalty",
        "or Executions",
        "or Killing Prisoners 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 10"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man's manager, \"Colonel\" Tom Parker, stopped him from playing Tony in the 1961 film adaptation of West Side Story. Ed Sullivan initially declared this man's performances \"unfit for family viewing\" after witnessing his \"gyrations\" during a performance on the Milton Berle Show. In 2019, the city of Memphis funded an expansion of this man's estate, Graceland. The \"King of Rock n' Roll\" was, for ten points, what Tennessee singer of Hound Dog\" and \"Heartbreak Hotel\"?",
      "answer": [
        "Elvis Presley or Elvis Aaron Presley",
        "either underline portion"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The Transnational Federal Government was formed in 2004 in this nation, which was led by Siad Barre [[SEE-add BAR-reh]] from 1969 until 1991. An American response to civil war in this nation turned disastrous when two Black Hawk helicopters were shot down. During the 2000s, this country was considered the home base of many pirates raiding shipping near the Gulf of Aden. For ten points, name this war-torn nation on the horn of Africa, once divided into British and Italian colonies.",
      "answer": "Somalia"
    },
    {
      "question": "This league's color barrier was broken in 1947 by Japanese-American Wataru Misaka. A coach in this league, Steve Kerr, came under fire in 2020 due to his comments about Hong Kong and the role of the Chinese government. In 2009, the owner of this league's Los Angeles Clippers was sued by former star Elgin Baylor on the grounds of racial discrimination. For ten points, name this league which mourned the death of Kobe Bryant in January 2020.",
      "answer": "National Basketball Association or NBA"
    },
    {
      "question": "Germany long resisted the implementation of this policy until the SPD made it the key point of coalition negotiations in 2013. A 1994 article by Alan Kreuger and David Card found that differences in this policy between New Jersey and Pennsylvania did not affect employment rates. This policy was first implemented in the U.S. by the Fair Labor Standards Act of 1938 and was last changed in 2007 at the federal level when it was set at $7.25. For ten points, name this lowest legally allowed rate for hourly labor compensation.",
      "answer": "Minimum wage"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man ironically published his memoir, Permanent Record, on September 17th which is also Constitution Day. This man is currently the head of the Board of Directors for the Freedom of the Press Foundation, having served in that role since 2016. In 2020, this man was finally granted asylum by the Russian government after fleeing the United States in 2013. For ten points, name this former NSA worker who leaked classified information about mass surveillance.",
      "answer": "Edward Snowden or Edward Joseph Snowden"
    },
    {
      "question": "The name of this location in the Canaima [[kah-NAY-muh]] National Park is derived from the American aviator who first surveyed it from an airplane. In 2009, Venezuelan president Hugo Chávez argued for reinstating this geographical feature’s indigenous name, Kerepakupai Merú [[keh-reh-pah-KOO-pye meh-ROO]], which means “waterfall of the deepest place.” For ten points, name this world’s tallest uninterrupted waterfall which measures 3,212 feet.",
      "answer": [
        "Angel Fallsor Salto Ángel ],",
        "Kerepakupai Merú ] before mentioned 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 8"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man and his wife made the first English translation of Agricola's Latin text on mining, De Rerum Metallica. He often conversed with his wife in Mandarin, and was the leader of Belgian food relief efforts after World War I. For 10 points, name this President who defeated Al Smith for election but suffered the start of the Great Depression in his first year in office.",
        "answer": "Herbert Hoover"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Hoover was born in which Midwestern state, where Barack Obama’s first presidential bid got a boost when he won its caucuses in 2008?",
        "answer": "Iowa"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "An advocate of this philosophy wrote The Great Divorce and the early feminist text Woman in the Nineteenth Century. This philosophy, whose journal The Dial was edited by Margaret Fuller, also included the man who wrote \"that government is best which governs least.\" For 10 points, name this philosophy of mid-nineteenth-century Americans such as Henry David Thoreau.",
        "answer": "transcendentalism"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What other transcendentalist delivered the lectures \"The American Scholar\" and \"Nature\" to audiences which were shocked by his apparent atheism?",
        "answer": "Ralph Waldo Emerson NHBB B 2014-2015"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A founder of this company is the namesake of a \"law\" stating that power doubles and price halves every eighteen months. This company purchased McAfee and Wind River and has been accused of using monopoly tactics against AMD. For 10 points, name this company which produces the Celeron, i7, and Pentium computer processors.",
        "answer": "Intel"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Intel became the chief supplier to what company after it abandoned the PowerPC architecture in 2006?",
        "answer": "Apple"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Journeys to this place are described in the Flatey Book. Karselfini clashed with residents of this place called \"Skraelings.\" An attempted colony in this place was discovered at the L'Anse aux Meadows site. A son of Eric the Red visited this place and dubbed it \"Vinland.\" For 10 points, name this continent visited by Leif Ericson nearly 500 years before Columbus's voyage.",
        "answer": "North America"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Lief Ericson’s father Eric the Red helped settle what island, where the Lawspeaker presided over the Althing parliament?",
        "answer": "Iceland NHBB B 2014-2015"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man responded to Barack Obama's Cairo address with the 2009 \"Bar-Ilan (BAR ee- LAHN) speech.\" He originally became prime minister after defeating Shimon Peres in a 1996 direct election, and has been in office again since forming a coalition against Tzipi Livni's Kadima (kah-DEE-muh) party. For 10 points, name this current prime minister of Israel.",
        "answer": "Benjamin \"Bibi\" Netanyahu"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Livni took over Kadima following the stroke which incapacitated what party founder, who pushed \"unilateral disengagement\" as PM in the early 2000s?",
        "answer": "Ariel Sharon"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "James Carleton launched a \"total war\" against this tribe, which was forced onto the \"Long Walk to Bosque Redondo\" by Kit Carson. In November 2014, this tribe's member Chester Nez died; Nez was the last surviving member of this tribe who worked as a \"code talker\" during World War II. For 10 points, name this large American Indian tribe in the Southwest.",
        "answer": "Navajo"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Navajo language has recently been shown to be distantly related to a group of languages spoken along the Yenisei River in what country?",
        "answer": "Russia"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Nancy Lopez was one of the most dominant athletes in this sport during the 1980’s, while former track star Babe Didrickson Zaharias also won numerous tournaments in this sport in the 1950’s. Se Ri Pak of South Korea achieved success in this sport at a young age, as did Michelle Wie, who competed in a series of events on the PGA tour. For 10 points, name this sport in which Annika Sörenstam made history in 2001 by shooting 59 in a competition round.",
        "answer": "golf"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Zaharias also won gold medals for the USA in track and field at the 1932 Olympics, which were held in which American city that also hosted the 1984 games?",
        "answer": "Los Angeles"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Brezhnev Doctrine was used to justify the invasion that ended this period of time. It began with its creator announcing “socialism with a human face.” Gustáv Husák replaced the leader who began this period, Alexander Dubček (DOOB-check), after the Warsaw Pact invasion deposed him. For 10 points, name this relaxing of one-party control in Czechoslovakia in 1968.",
        "answer": "Prague Spring"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What country led by Enver Hoxha left the Warsaw Pact over the decision to invade Czechoslovakia?",
        "answer": "Albania NHBB B 2014-2015"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In October 2014, a court case was filed regarding a Firestone rubber plantation in this\ncountry's town of Harbel. This country was the origin of Thomas Eric Duncan, who infected two\nnurses after arriving in Dallas with ebola. For 10 points, name this country where president Ellen\nJohnson Sirleaf governs the descendants of resettled American slaves.",
        "answer": [
          "Liberia",
          "Republic of Liberia"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The 2014 ebola outbreak began in what northern neighbor of Liberia with capital at\nConakry, which had its first-ever democratic presidential election in 2010?",
        "answer": [
          "Guinea",
          "Republic of Guinea"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This color names a \"democratic movement\" which supports former Kenyan prime minister\nRaila Odinga (rah-EE-luh oh-DING-guh). A river separating both Namibia and Lesotho from\nSouth Africa is named for this color, which inspired a \"free state\" in pre-union South Africa. For\n10 points, name this color also used for the Dutch royal house and a citrus fruit.",
        "answer": "orange"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The 2004 Orange Revolution protested vote-rigging by Viktor Yanukovych (YAHnik-oh-vitch) in what country?",
        "answer": "Ukraine"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This event was a failure of Brigade 2506, which landed at Playa Giron (hee-ROAN). Allen\nDulles took most of the blame for this event, which was a CIA operation with inadequate\nmilitary support. This event relied mostly on exiles and prompted its target to formally ally with\nthe Soviets. For 10 points, name this failed 1961 invasion of Cuba authorized by JFK.",
        "answer": [
          "Bay of Pigs invasion",
          "Bay of Pigs"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What Florida senator of Cuban descent, sometimes mentioned as a possible 2016\npresidential candidate, criticized the 2014 agreement to partially lift sanctions against Cuba?",
        "answer": [
          "Marco Rubio",
          "Rubio"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This product was named by Rowland Hanson, who shot down the proposed name \"Interface\nManager.\" In 1992, this product's manufacturer decided to focus on it and stop developing OS/2.\nThis product's popular versions included 3.1, NT, and 95, prior to the release of version 7 in\n2009. For 10 points, name this operating system produced by Microsoft.",
        "answer": "Windows"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "OS/2 was a joint project of Microsoft and what former titan of the industry, known as\n\"Big Blue\" for the color of both its logo and its once-mandatory employee ties?",
        "answer": "IBM"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Martial law was declared in this nation after the First Quarter Storm. Cardinal Jaime Sin\nhelped spearhead the overthrow of one leader of this nation. That leader’s wife had a massive\ncollection of shoes, which was left behind after the People’s Power Revolution. For 10 points,\nname this Asian nation which was formerly ruled by Ferdinand Marcos.",
        "answer": "the Philippines"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Philippines was devastated by Yolanda in 2013, a kind of which storm?",
        "answer": "Typhoon"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The losing Democratic candidate in this state's 2014 race sought to become the first Iraq war veteran to serve as a governor and lost to a ticket containing Boyd Rutherford, the third straight black lieutenant governor in this state. For 10 points, name this state where Anthony Brown lost in an upset to Republican Lawrence Hogan in a bid to succeed Martin O'Malley as governor.",
        "answer": "Maryland"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Anthony Brown's wife is the director of government relations for what media conglomerate, the owner of NBC and Universal Studios, which entered FCC scrutiny in 2014 after announcing plans to purchase Time Warner Cable?",
        "answer": "Comcast"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 2009, voters approved an amendment in this organization's constitution that replaced the unanimity requirement with a “double majority” requirement for many policies. The Maastricht Treaty created this group and gave the criteria necessary for countries to adopt its common currency. For 10 points, name this organization of sovereign states, many of whom use the euro.",
        "answer": "European Union"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What capital city was the namesake for the treaty signed in 2007 and approved in 2009 that changed the voting procedure for the Council of Ministers?",
        "answer": "Lisbon"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Mark Kurlansky's popular-press World History of this good describes how the Taghaza mine produced it in the medieval Sahara desert. This chemical compound was traded in silence in pre- modern West Africa, where its value per pound was equal to a pound of gold. For 10 points, name this mineral which was useful for preserving meat and balancing diets.",
        "answer": "rock salt"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What empire, which presided over the salt-for-gold trade from Kumbi Saleh, had its name adopted by Kwame Nkrumah for the post-independence Gold Coast?",
        "answer": "Ghana Empire NHBB B 2014-2015"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 2014, a letter from this person to George Putnam was discovered showing her interest in a nonconventional marriage. This member of the Ninety-Nines achieved fame after landing in Northern Ireland, and later departed with Fred Noonan on a trip that was last tracked at Howland Island. For 10 points, name this aviatrix who disappeared in 1937 over the Pacific.",
        "answer": "Amelia Earhart"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What American humorist and Ziegfield Follies star also died in a plane crash, and quipped \"I'm not a member of any organized party. I'm a Democrat?\"",
        "answer": "Will Rogers"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man briefly served as governor of California during the Civil War, in a term whose most distinguishing event was his rowing a boat down flooded streets in order to attend his inauguration. He paid Edward Muybridge to take important photographs of running horses. For 10 points, name this Central Pacific Railroad head and namesake of a Palo Alto university.",
        "answer": "Leland Stanford"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Leland Stanford drove in the \"Golden Spike\" at what Utah site, completing the Transcontinental Railroad?",
        "answer": "Promontory Point NHBB B 2014-2015"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This organization was targeted in November 2014 by the hashtag \"Things That Are Not Mosques\" after it erroneously identified Westminster Cathedral as a mosque. This organization, which is represented in polling maps by the color purple, is led by former metal commodities trader Nigel Farage. For 10 points, name this right-wing party that is surging in the U.K.",
        "answer": "UKIP"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "UKIP is currently polling as the third most popular party in the U.K., displacing what coalition partner of the Conservatives led by Deputy Prime Minister Nick Clegg?",
        "answer": "Liberal Democrats"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This woman hosted the reality show Mr. Personality and wrote the 2014 article \"Shame and Survival,\" which continues her criticism of her depiction in the book My Life. This employee of the Office of Legislative Affairs was secretly taped by Linda Tripp, who referred her to Kenneth Starr. For 10 points, identify this namesake of a sex scandal in the Clinton administration.",
        "answer": "Monica Lewinsky"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Lewinsky scandal was revealed four years after what Arkansas civil servant sued President Clinton for a 1991 sexual harassment incident?",
        "answer": "Paula Jones NHBB B 2014-2015"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man popularized the term \"NASCAR dads\" to explain the type of voter he wished to appeal to in addition to \"soccer moms.\" He designed the \"fifty-state strategy\" as head of the Democratic National Committee, which was a more successful effort than his own Presidential campaign. For 10 points, name this Vermont political who was embarrassed by a 2004 \"scream.\"",
        "answer": "Howard Dean"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What rival of Dean for the 2004 Democratic nomination was the former Supreme Commander of NATO who oversaw the 1999 Kosovo War?",
        "answer": "Wesley Clark"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 1997, this man succeeded Lionel Jospin (juice-PAN) as head of the Socialist Party, a post he held for a decade until his longtime partner Ségolène Royal (say-go-LEN roy-AL) lost a presidential election. In January 2014, he suffered a scandal over his relationship with Julie Gayet (guy-EH). For 10 points, name this current president of France.",
        "answer": "François Hollande"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Hollande succeeded what leader of the UMP as president in 2012 after defeating his re- election bid?",
        "answer": "Nicolas Sarközy"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "These people's kings performed a ritual in which they drew blood with a barbed cord, in order to worship their gods such as Chac. These people's mythology, which centered on the descent of the Hero Twins to the underworld Xibalba (shib-ALL-buh) to play the \"ball game,\" is collected in the Popul Vuh. For 10 points, name this Meso-American group that built Chichen Itza.",
        "answer": "Mayans"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Tikal site of Mayan ruins is found in what English-speaking country?",
        "answer": "Belize NHBB B 2014-2015"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Minnesota case of Baker v. Nelson upheld a statute forbidding this action. The 12th anniversary of Lawrence v. Texas coincided with the decision in a Supreme Court case that legalized this practice. U.S. v. Windsor struck down Section 3 of DOMA, which allowed states to reject these events until 2013. For ten points, name this social right made legal in all 50 states by 2015’s Obergefell v Hodges.",
        "answer": [
          "same-sex marriage or gay marriage",
          "descriptive answers"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Kim Davis, a clerk from this state, refused to issue marriage licenses after the Obergefell decision due to personal beliefs.",
        "answer": "Kentucky"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "While attempting to perform this action, David Sharp died near the corpse of “Green Boots,” which was visible from 2006 until his burial in 2014. The Japanese comedian Ayako Imoto gave up her effort to do this after a 2014 disaster on the Khumbu Icefall. When asked why he would attempt this action, George Mallory responded, “Because it’s there.” Tenzing Norgay and Edmund Hillary were the first recorded people to perform, for ten points, what landmark feat in mountaineering in Nepal?",
        "answer": [
          "Climbing Mt. Everest",
          "descriptions"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This author’s Into Thin Air described his experiences in a 1996 disaster on Everest. His Into the Wild describes the disappearance and death of Christopher McCandless.",
        "answer": "Jon Krakauer"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The “Cactus Curtain” surrounds this facility, for which only one lease check has been cashed. Thomson Correctional Center is currently being prepared to replace this location. In 2011, Wikileaks released files on 765 of the 779 prisoners then kept at this location. President Obama made a campaign pledge to close, for ten points, what U.S. military prison located on a Cuban bay, notorious for torture and violations of human rights?",
        "answer": "Guantanamo Bay Naval Base"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In Hamdan v. this man, then the Secretary of Defense for the Bush Administration, the Supreme Court ruled that Article 3 of the Geneva Conventions still applied. This man once described a theory of “known knowns” and “unknown unknowns.”",
        "answer": "Donald Rumsfeld"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A 1978 measure in this state restricted property-tax reassessments, and in 1994 it passed a referendum barring unauthorized immigrants from receiving social services. This state, which passed Propositions 13 and 187, was once governed by Pete Wilson and conducted a 2003 recall election which removed Democrat Gray Davis from office. For ten points, name this Western state which Arnold Schwarzenegger led for eight years from Sacramento.",
        "answer": "California"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This current governor of California also led the state from 1975 to 1983, during which time he was nicknamed “Governor Moonbeam.”",
        "answer": "Edmund Gerald “Jerry” Brown"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One leader of this group reportedly lost his right eye at the Battle of Arghandab in 1987 and died of tuberculosis in 2013. This group did not announce that leader’s death until 2015 and is disputing reports that his replacement, Akhtar Mansoor, was killed in December 2015. Mullah Muhammad Omar led this organization and was President of its home country until 2001’s Operation Enduring Freedom. For ten points, name this Islamic insurgent group that once controlled Afghanistan.",
        "answer": "Taliban"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Taliban is funded largely by smuggling of this substance, which is harvested by making small cuts in poppy seed pods and then processed into a variety of drugs, including heroin.",
        "answer": "opium"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Joel Klein was the leading prosecutor in a case involving this company, which involved restrictive licensing agreements with OEMs. It was forced to share its APIs with third-party companies in the settlement of its case. Paul Maritz, an employee of this company, was quoted as wanting to “extinguish” Netscape during testimony concerning this company’s potential monopolistic behavior in its bundling of Internet Explorer. For ten points, name this software company founded by Bill Gates.",
        "answer": [
          "Microsoft",
          "U.S. v. Microsoft"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This lawyer represented the states in U.S. v. Microsoft before being appointed to the D.C. Circuit in 2003. This Supreme Court justice typically votes with Scalia, Thomas, and Alito to uphold conservative rulings.",
        "answer": "John G. Roberts"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "At a 2015 award ceremony, an actor impersonated this man threatening to kill Hannibal Buress. This man resigned from the board of Temple University, his alma mater, in 2014. In a 2005 deposition, this man admitted to illegally giving the sedative Quaalude to at least one woman. For ten points, name this actor and comedian who played Cliff Huxtable on a 1980s sitcom and has been accused by over 50 women of sexual assault.",
        "answer": "Bill Cosby"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This voice of Donkey in the Shrek films and former Saturday Night Live comedian did the aforementioned Bill Cosby impression while accepting the 2015 Mark Twain Prize for American Humor.",
        "answer": "Eddie Murphy"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This game was played at BC Place on artificial turf after a lawsuit requesting natural grass was droppped. A 60-yard strike over Ayumi Kaihori in the 16th minute was the fourth of seven goals in this game, in which Christie Rampone and Abby Wambach subbed on in the second half. A hat trick by Carli Lloyd sealed, for ten points, what 2015 soccer tournament won by the United States over Japan?",
        "answer": [
          "2015 FIFA Women’s World Cup final match",
          "equivalents describing the championship game of the 2015 FIFA Women’s World Cup"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This USA goalie won the 2015 Women’s World Cup Golden Glove as the top goalie in the tournament, shortly after having been suspended from the team for her domestic violence arrest.",
        "answer": "Hope Solo"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Members of this class were often expected to master both the bun and the bu, and some of these people used weapons made by the 14th century steelsmith Masamune [mass-uh-moo-nay]. This class was replaced with a conscripted army following the Boshin War, which brought Emperor Meiji [may-jee] to power and ended the Tokugawa Shogunate. For ten points, name these medieval Japanese warriors.",
        "answer": "samurai accept, but do not otherwise reveal, bushi"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The name of this Shinto-inspired code of samurai chivalry translates to “way of the warrior.”",
        "answer": "bushido"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man accused Mitch McConnell of telling an “out-right lie” with regards to the Export-Import Bank. He criticized the Obama administration’s handling of the death of Darren Goforth, a sheriff’s deputy in this man’s state. This successor to Kay Bailey Hutchinson filibustered the Affordable Care Act in 2013 shortly after being elected as the junior Senator from Texas. For ten points, name this Republican senator and 2016 Presidential candidate.",
        "answer": "Ted Cruz"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Ted Cruz served as a clerk to this Supreme Court Justice who, as a law clerk, defended Plessy v. Ferguson in an infamous 1952 memo.",
        "answer": "William Rehnquist"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This figure provided the advice to travel through what are now called the Gibbons and Bozeman Passes; that advice was given to colleagues met at Fort Mandan. As a child, this sister of Camheawait was kidnapped by the Hidatsa, from whom she was purchased by Toussaint Charbonneau. This woman was honored in 2000 with the minting of a dollar coin. The Corps of Exploration was aided by, for ten points, what woman, a Shoshone [sho-sho-ne] guide who assisted Lewis and Clark?",
        "answer": "Sacagawea"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Lewis and Clark met Sacagawea and Charbonneau at Fort Mandan, which the Corps built in North Dakota on this river, which they became the first to entirely travel.",
        "answer": "Missouri River"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In this state, Charles Brooks was killed by lethal injection, the first such execution in the world. In 1998 in this state, three white supremacists killed James Byrd, Jr. by dragging him behind a truck through Jasper. One of Byrd’s murderers refused to eat a lavish last meal, after which this state ended its practice of completing special requests for the condemned. For ten points, name this state that, since 1976, has carried out more than one-third of American criminal executions, including under Governors Rick Perry and George W. Bush.",
        "answer": "Texas"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A 2009 expansion of federal hate crime legislation was named for the aforementioned James Byrd and Matthew Shepard; in 1998, Shepard was tortured and left to die in this state’s town of Laramie.",
        "answer": "Wyoming"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Second Manifesto represented a shift away from this practice, which was ruled illegal in the case of Reynolds v. United States. Wilford Woodruff issued an 1890 declaration against this practice. In 2008, the YFZ Ranch in Texas was raided for practicing this tradition as part of a fundamentalist version of the Mormon faith, which turned away from this practice despite Joseph Smith and Brigham Young’s acceptance of it. For ten points, name this marital practice of taking more than one spouse.",
        "answer": [
          "polygamy",
          "descriptions before “taking more” is read"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "During oral arguments in this 2015 Supreme Court case, Justices Alito, Scalia, and Roberts all made comments claiming that this decision could be used to justify plural marriages. This decision did overturn Baker v. Nelson.",
        "answer": "Obergefell v. Hodges"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this event in 2015, 107 people were killed by a crane collapse, while a stampede in 1990 killed over 1,400 participants. This event commemorates the seeking of water by Hajar, who ran between the hills of Safa and Marwah seven times; that path is now enclosed by the Masjid al-Haram. Other rituals that take place during this annual event include tawaf, in which one walks around the Kaaba. For ten points, name this pillar of Islam, requiring an annual pilgrimage to Mecca.",
        "answer": "hajj"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The water sought by Hagar and drunk by pilgrims on hajj comes from this well, within the Masjid al-Haram.",
        "answer": "Zamzam Well"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One politician from this state refused to re-certify the President’s Surveillance Program from his hospital bed while serving as George W. Bush’s first Attorney General. This is the home state of John Ashcroft, as well as a Democratic Senate candidate who assembled an AR-15 rifle while blindfolded in a 2016 campaign ad; that man, Jason Kander, lost to incumbent Senator Roy Blunt. Claire McCaskill also serves, for ten points, what Midwestern state where Eric Greitens serves as governor in Jefferson City?",
        "answer": "Missouri"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This mid-20th century politician served ten years as Senator from Missouri before serving less than three months as Vice President.",
        "answer": "Harry S Truman"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In the aftermath of this event, Governor Kathleen Blanco emphasized that National Guardsmen were armed with M-16s and would “shoot and kill.” Two unarmed civilians were killed by police at Danziger Bridge after this disaster. Michael Brown was told he was “doing a heck of a job” dealing with the devastation wrought by this event before he was fired from his post as Director of FEMA by George W. Bush. For ten points, name this 2005 natural disaster, a hurricane that devastated New Orleans and the Gulf Coast.",
        "answer": "Hurricane Katrina"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Army Corps of Engineers determined that most of the lives lost in New Orleans during Katrina were the result of the failure of these earthen protections, 53 of which were breeched by the storm surge.",
        "answer": [
          "levees",
          "dikes",
          "floodbanks"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Charles Tyson Yerkes thwarted this man’s efforts to build part of the London Underground through London United Tramways. This man founded New York’s Metropolitan Club and orchestrated a business deal with Elbert Gary and William Henry Moore in 1901. This man created a coalition of bankers to mitigate the Panic of 1907; earlier, he allied with the Rothschilds to sell gold to replenish the US Treasury during the Panic of 1893. For ten points, name this American financier, the namesake of a bank that merged with Chase in 2000.",
        "answer": "John Pierpont “J.P.” Morgan, Sr."
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "J.P. Morgan transformed this industry with the aforementioned merger of Judge Moore’s company with one owned by Andrew Carnegie, creating the world’s first billion-dollar business.",
        "answer": [
          "steel",
          "any additional information, including US Steel"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A speech given by this man claims that, though Cassius Clay could also sing, it was swinging that made him a world champion. In 2010, Thomas Hagan was formally paroled for his murder of this man, who gave the “Ballot or the Bullet” speech in 1964. This man took the name name Detroit Red as a criminal; while imprisoned for robbery, he adopted the teachings of Elijah Muhammad. For ten points, name this civil rights activist and member of Nation of Islam who replaced his given surname Little with a single letter.",
        "answer": "Malcolm X"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Malcolm X and Elijah Muhammad both taught this current leader of the Nation of Islam, who organized the Million Man March on Washington in 1995.",
        "answer": [
          "Louis Farrakhan",
          "Louis Walcott"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A governor of this state was chairman of Hillary Clinton’s 2008 bid for the presidency and controversially tried to restore the voting rights of more than 200,000 felons in an executive order that was later overturned. Democratic blocs in Fairfax and Arlington counties have made this state increasingly blue in recent elections. A senator from this state was chosen as the running mate for Hillary Clinton in the 2016 presidential election. Tim Kaine represents, for ten points, what state where state law prevents governors from serving consecutive terms in Richmond?",
        "answer": "Virginia"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This aforementioned governor of Virginia was succeeded by Ralph Northam in 2018.",
        "answer": "Terry McAuliffe"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Hekla 3 Eruption may have caused the end of this period. The Yamna Culture existed during the early stages of this period. The Hittites and Mycenaeans fell apart during this period’s namesake collapse. This period was the second in a classification scheme laid out by the antiquarian Christian Thomsen based on the artifacts used by people at the time. For ten points, name this period that succeeded the Stone Age and preceded the Iron Age.",
        "answer": "Bronze Age"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Among the cities to be destroyed during the Bronze Age collapse were Kadesh, Karkemish, and Ugarit, all of which lie on the shores or borders of this modern day country. In 2015, this country’s ancient ruins in Palmyra were heavily damaged during its civil war.",
        "answer": "Syria"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This monarch was crowned under the statute Titulus Regius after ordering the arrest of Earl Rivers. This ruler claimed that his predecessor’s marriage to Elizabeth Woodville was illegitimate and took the throne after supposedly ordering James Tyrell to murder the Princes in the Tower. This man was slain at the Battle of Bosworth Field, making him the final Plantagenet ruler. For ten points, name this king from the House of York during the War of the Roses.",
        "answer": "Richard III"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 2012, an excavation discovered Richard III’s remains under a parking lot in this English city.",
        "answer": "Leicester"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "V´ıctor Huggo Martin portrayed this man in a David Attwood miniseries a year after this man’s Untold Story was released as a documentary by Estela Bravo. Prior to his interviews with Hugo Chavez and Vladimir Putin, Oliver Stone released two documentaries of interviews with this man: a 2004 film Looking for him, and a 2003 film titled just Comandante. A 2006 BBC documentary reviewed the alleged 638 ways in which the CIA attempted to assassinate, for ten points, what longtime dictator of Cuba?",
        "answer": "Fidel Castro"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In the 2002 miniseries Fidel, Gael Garcia Bernal played what other revolutionary, a role that he reprised in the 2004 film The Motorcycle Diaries?",
        "answer": "Ernesto “Che” Guevara"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A global database of incidents of this phenomenon is maintained by the research group START at the University of Maryland. Samuel Scheffler distinguishes “general” and “state” types of this phenonmenon in a 2006 paper, and Robert Pape analyzes the strategic logic of this phenomenon in his 2005 book Dying to Win. This phenomenon’s name can be traced back to the French Revolution, during the so-called “reign” of Robespierre. For ten points, name this phenomenon, broadly defined as intentional violence to coerce or incite fear, as exemplified by the September 11 attacks.",
        "answer": "terrorism"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Samuel Scheffler’s “Is Terrorism Morally Distinctive?” discusses this thinker, who characterized fear as the “worst incommodity of all” in a passage that ends by describing the life of man as “solitary, poor, nasty, brutish, and short” in the state of nature.",
        "answer": "Thomas Hobbes"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A star fort in this state called Fort Elizabeth was built by Georg Anton Schaffer, an agent of the Russian-American Company. An observatory in this state is named for deceased astronaut Ellison Onizuka. This state, which grows nearly half of the world’s macadamia nuts, contains sites like the Bernice Bishop Museum and Iolani Palace. For ten points, name this US state that was once a kingdom united by Kamehameha I in the Pacific Ocean.",
        "answer": "Hawaii"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This sacred dormant volcano, Hawaii’s highest point, was the site of 2015 protests over the creation of the Thirty Meter Telescope.",
        "answer": "Mauna Kea"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 2006, this man was ultimately convicted of insider trading in Soci´et´e G´en´erale, a French bank that he had invested in in 1988. This man made over a billion dollars on September 16, 1992, known as Black Wednesday, because this man held a ten billion dollar short position on the pound; as a result, he became known as “the man who broke the Bank of England.” Charter 77 and Solidarity were among the political groups funded by this man, who has been a common target of American right-wing pundits and anti-Semites. For ten points, name this Hungarian born founder of the philanthropic Open Society Foundations, a liberal activist and investor.",
        "answer": "George Soros"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Prime Minister of Malaysia blamed “a Jew” - implied to be Soros - for destroying his country’s economy in 1997.",
        "answer": "Mahathir bin Mohamad"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This king captured 120 standards, today found at Riddarholm Church. Finnish troops serving under this man were called Hakkapelitta or \"Cut them down!\" Lennart Torestensson helped this man catch the Tercios of the Count of Tilly. Gustav Horn served this ruler, who rode the war horse Streiff without wearing armor and was killed in the fog at Lützen [[LOOH-tzen]]. This man won at the Battles of Lech and Breitenfeld in the Thirty Years' War. For ten points, name this Vasa king of Sweden.",
        "answer": [
          "Gustavus Adolphus",
          "Gustav II Adolph"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This daughter of Gustavus Adolphus abdicated her throne in 1654 when she converted to Catholicism and is one of the few women buried in the Vatican grotto.",
        "answer": "Christina, Queen of Sweden 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Round 3"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This woman was mentored by gospel singers Clara Ward and Mahalia Jackson after her mother died. This woman’s first Top Ten pop hit, “I Never Loved A Man (The Way I Love You)” was recorded at FAME Studios in Muscle Shoals, and among her 16 other Top Ten hits in the US were “Think” and “Who’s Zoomin’ Who.” In 1987, this singer became the first woman inducted into the Rock and Roll Hall of Fame. “Chain of Fools” and “(You Make Me Feel) Like A Natural Woman” are award-winning songs by, for ten points, what woman known as the Queen of Soul?",
        "answer": "Aretha Franklin"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The 2021 Coretta Scott King Illustrator Award went to Frank Morrison for his work on a biography of Aretha Franklin named for what feminist anthem that repeatedly spells out its title?",
        "answer": "Respect 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Round 5"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Wool taxes to restore one of these structures led to legends that it was built on wool packs. The start of the pilgrimage trail to Canterbury began at one of these structures built in 1209. On that iteration of these structures, many buildings such as the Nonsuch House were located as were the displayed heads of traitors like William Wallace. Oilman Robert McCulloch brought a version of this structure to Lake Havasu City in Arizona. For ten points, by what name are all of these bridges across the Thames known, one of which is \"Falling down\"?",
        "answer": "London Bridge"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "London Bridge was furnished with red lights for a 2004 flyover celebration by wartime aircraft on this British holiday, observed since the end of World War One in memory of fallen armed service members.",
        "answer": [
          "Remembrance Day",
          "Poppy Day 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Playoff Round 1"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This person nominated Harriet Miers to the Supreme Court, and under his administration, Scooter Libby was implicated in the Valerie Plame Affair. This president devised the No Child Left Behind Act. This man also landed on the USS Abraham Lincoln and gave the “Mission Accomplished” speech, despite the fact that the Iraq War was still being fought. This man declared, \"I can hear you\" when speaking to first responders while standing next to a fireman with a bull horn. For ten points, name this US president from Texas who faced 9/11.",
        "answer": [
          "George Walker Bush",
          "Bush 43"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "George W. Bush helped make Texas the leading producer of this form of energy. This type of energy is collected at locations like Los Vientos and Tehachapi Pass in large \"farms.\"",
        "answer": [
          "Wind power",
          "descriptive answers indicating power",
          "electricity produced by wind"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "To build the hydrogen bomb, this company built and operated the Savannah River Site. This company created a brochure called \"Farming with Dynamite\" which promoted using explosives to remove obstacles. This company began by making gunpowder at the Eleutherian Mills for the US Army. This company created the ozone layer-damaging chlorofluorocarbon Freon. Some of this company's products include a material for nonstick pans, Teflon, as well as the polymer Nylon. For ten points, name this Delaware-based chemical company.",
        "answer": [
          "E.I. DuPont de Nemours and Company",
          "DuPont de Nemours, Inc."
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 2017, the original duPont company merged with this other chemical company that was boycotted during the Vietnam War for its production of napalm.",
        "answer": "The Dow Chemical Company"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man became chairman of SNCC [[SNIK]] in 1963, after which James Forman rewrote a speech by this man to read, \"We support [the Kennedy civil rights bill] with great reservations.” This man was the first of the Freedom Riders to be attacked while at Rock Hill and accused Julian Bond of using cocaine en route to being elected to the House. As one of the \"Big 6\" in the March on Washington, this man led the Selma to Montgomery Marches, being attacked on Bloody Sunday. For ten points, name this Civil Rights leader from Georgia who passed away in 2020.",
        "answer": "John Lewis"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "John Lewis was succeeded as Chairman of SNCC [[SNIK]] by this man, a fellow Freedom Rider, who later became \"Honorary Prime Minister\" of the Black Panthers, moved to Africa, and changed his name to Kwame Ture.",
        "answer": "Stokely Carmichael"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This city was the center of the Affair of the Placards, which resulted from rising tensions between Catholics and Protestants. In 1871, over ten thousand people were massacred when a \"Commune\" in this city was brutally crushed. The wildcat strikes of May, 1968 were centered on this city's student population. In November 2015, an ISIS attack at a soccer stadium and the Bataclan Theatre led to over a hundred deaths in this city. For ten points, name this French city where Notre Dame caught fire in 2019.",
        "answer": [
          "Paris",
          "Paris Commune"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This world-famous Parisian museum was closed for six months at the beginning of the Covid-19 pandemic in France. It occupies a former palace used primarily for military activities.",
        "answer": "Louvre ] Museum or Louvre Palace"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The southern portion of this historical kingdom was ceded to the British in the Simla Accords. The warlord Ma Bufang held a future leader of this kingdom hostage until a ransom of Silver Dragon coins was paid. The Seventeen Points Agreement was negotiated between this kingdom's leader, Tenzin Gyatso, and the government of Mao Zedong. The Dalai Lama [[DAH-lee LAH-muh]] leads the government-in-exile of, for ten points, what historical kingdom currently controlled by China?",
        "answer": [
          "Kingdom of Tibet",
          "Bod ]",
          "Xīzàng"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Most Tibetans follows a regional variation of this faith which adheres to the teachings of Siddhartha Gautama.",
        "answer": [
          "Buddhism",
          "Tibetan Buddhism",
          "Tantric Buddhism",
          "Mahayana Buddhism 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 1"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A statue of this man was commissioned in the United States for the thousandth anniversary of the Althing. The tale of the lost merchant Bjarni Herjólfsson [[BYAR-nee hare-YOHLF-son]] inspired this man to travel west. This explorer encountered the Skraelings [[SKRAY-lings]], who killed his brother Thorvald in a skirmish outside of L'Anse aux Meadows [[LAHN see MEH-doh]]. The region of Vinland was discovered by, for ten points, which Norse explorer and son of Erik the Red?",
        "answer": [
          "Leif Erikson",
          "Leif the Lucky",
          "or Leifr hinn Heppni"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Leif Erikson's father, Erik the Red, is credited with founding the first European settlement on this large semi-arctic island, which in 2009 became autonomous from Denmark.",
        "answer": [
          "Greenland",
          "Kalaallit Nunaat",
          "or Grønland"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One leader of this nation launched the Infitah [[in-fee-TAH]] policy, which \"opened the door\" to western investment. During a parade celebrating Operation Badr [[BAD-er]] in this nation, that leader was assassinated by members of the Islamic Jihad. Protests in this country's Tahrir Square in 2011 led to the ousting of long-time president Hosni Mubarak. Since 2014, Abdel Fattah el-Sisi has served as president of, for ten points, what Arab nation governed from Cairo?",
        "answer": "Egypt"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "During Operation Badr, the Egyptian Army captured part of the Sinai [[\"SIGH\"-nye]] Peninsula from this Middle Eastern neighbor, led at the time by Golda Meir [[GOHL-duh may-EER]].",
        "answer": [
          "Israel or Yisra'el",
          "State of Israel",
          "or Medinat Yisra'el"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The peace treaty ending this war led to a fifteen month \"Interim Peace\" and ceded one side's second-largest city of Viipuri [[VEE-poo-ree]]. This war saw the invention of Molotov [[MOH-loh-tohff]] cocktails. During this war, one side employed ski soldiers and a man called \"White Death,\" Simo Häyhä [[SEE-moh HY-ah]]. Despite taking Karelia [[kah- REH-lyah]], the Soviets failed to reach Helsinki in, for ten points, what World War Two-era conflict which saw Finland maintain its independence?",
        "answer": "Winter War"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "During the Winter War, the Finns utilized a defensive line named for what German- descended commander-in-chief who led the White forces in the Finnish Civil War?",
        "answer": "Carl Gustaf Emil Mannerheim 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 8"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "After failing to provide the donativum to this organization, a rogue member of it slashed the throat of Pertinax. This organization auctioned off the title of imperator, eventually bestowing the title to Didius Julianus for 25,000 sesterces. Earlier that year, this elite unit's prefect paid off Narcissus to kill his wrestling partner, Emperor Commodus. For ten points, name this imperial bodyguard who often interfered in Roman politics.",
        "answer": [
          "Praetorian Guard",
          "Praetorian Cohort",
          "Cohortēs praetōriae"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Praetorian Guard was dissolved after Constantine the Great defeated Maxentius at this battle, where Constantine supposedly painted a Chi Rho [[KYE ROH]] on the shields of his soldiers.",
        "answer": [
          "Battle of Milvian Bridge",
          "Battle of Ponte Milvio 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 9"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 2015, in the area surrounding this waterway, an Economic Zone was established with custom rates set at zero as part of a larger \"Area Development Project.\" Operation Musketeer was a planned invasion of this structure by Britain and France, which occurred during a \"Crisis\" around this structure's nationalization by Gamel Abdel Nasser. For ten points, name this waterway that connects the Mediterranean Sea and the Red Sea.",
        "answer": "Suez Canal"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Israelis commonly refer to the Suez Crisis as a war for this continent-connecting peninsula located in eastern Egypt.",
        "answer": "Sinai Peninsula or Sīna"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "ANDREW JACKSON",
      "prompt": "Name the andrew jackson...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Represented what political party?",
          "answer": "Democrats"
        },
        {
          "question": "Currently appears on what denomination of currency?",
          "answer": "twenty-dollar bill"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ordered the removal of Cherokee on what \"trail?\"",
          "answer": "Trail of Tears"
        },
        {
          "question": "Campaigned for what \"dark horse\" to be elected in 1844?",
          "answer": "James Knox Polk"
        },
        {
          "question": "Opposed what kind of institution's national charter?",
          "answer": "national bank"
        },
        {
          "question": "Won the Battle of New Orleans two weeks after what treaty was signed?",
          "answer": "Treaty of Ghent"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was scandalized by the snubbing of a Cabinet member's wife in what \"affair?\"",
          "answer": "Eaton affair"
        },
        {
          "question": "Owned a home that shared its name with what Russian art museum?",
          "answer": "The Hermitage NHBB B 2014-2015"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "SUPREME COURT JUSTICES",
      "prompt": "What Supreme Court Justice…",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Oversaw the desegregation of schools in Brown v. Board?",
          "answer": "Earl Warren"
        },
        {
          "question": "Is the current Chief Justice?",
          "answer": "John Roberts"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the first black Justice, appointed in 1967?",
          "answer": "Thurgood Marshall"
        },
        {
          "question": "Established the principle of judicial review in Marbury v. Madison?",
          "answer": "John Marshall"
        },
        {
          "question": "Survived the Anita Hill hearings in 1991?",
          "answer": "Clarence Thomas"
        },
        {
          "question": "Delivered the Dred Scott decision?",
          "answer": "Roger Taney"
        },
        {
          "question": "Is the current \"swing vote\" in many rulings?",
          "answer": "Anthony Kennedy"
        },
        {
          "question": "Wrote the Roe v. Wade decision after research at the Mayo Clinic?",
          "answer": "Harry Blackmun NHBB B 2014-2015"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "ALASKA",
      "prompt": "Name the alaska...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Admitted to the U.S. in 1959, eight months before what 50th state?",
          "answer": "Hawaii"
        },
        {
          "question": "The home of Larry Sanger, who co-founded what online encyclopedia with Jimbo Wales?",
          "answer": "Wikipedia"
        },
        {
          "question": "The site of a 1964 earthquake which struck on what holiday two days before Easter?",
          "answer": "Good Friday"
        },
        {
          "question": "The site of a 1989 disaster when what oil company's tanker Valdez crashed on Prince William Sound?",
          "answer": "Exxon"
        },
        {
          "question": "The destination of the central animated family, which flees Springfield, in what 2007 film?",
          "answer": "The Simpsons Movie"
        },
        {
          "question": "Represented in the Senate from 1968 to 2009 by what longest-tenured Republican Senator ever?",
          "answer": "Ted Stevens"
        },
        {
          "question": "Embarrassed when that Senator used what three-word phrase to describe the Internet in a 2006 viral video?",
          "answer": "\"series of tubes\""
        },
        {
          "question": "Home to a proposed accessway to Gravina Island which received what derogatory nickname in a 2006 debate over pork-barrel spending?",
          "answer": "\"bridge to nowhere\""
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "MESOAMERICA BEFORE COLUMBUS",
      "prompt": "Before Europeans arrived, indigenous people in the Americas…",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "grew \"ears\" of what crop bred from the wild grass teosinte?",
          "answer": "corn"
        },
        {
          "question": "mined what green precious stone also found in China?",
          "answer": "jade"
        },
        {
          "question": "sculpted what human features from stone at Olmec sites like La Venta?",
          "answer": "heads"
        },
        {
          "question": "Denoted what number with a shell glyph long before Europeans used it in calculations?",
          "answer": "zero"
        },
        {
          "question": "built what Yucatan peninsula site home to a big step pyramid?",
          "answer": "Chichén Itzá"
        },
        {
          "question": "used what reckoning systems such as the Mayan baktun and the Aztec Sun Stone?",
          "answer": "calendars"
        },
        {
          "question": "wrote what preserved books, such as a Maya example now named for Dresden?",
          "answer": "codex"
        },
        {
          "question": "built arenas for what sacred activity which used players' hips and feet, and stone hoops?",
          "answer": "Mesoamerican sacred ball game NHBB B 2014-2015"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "GAMAL ABDEL NASSER",
      "prompt": "Who or what was…",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "The nation ruled by Nasser until his death from a heart attack?",
          "answer": "Egypt"
        },
        {
          "question": "Military officer who succeeded Nasser to the Presidency?",
          "answer": "Anwar Sadat"
        },
        {
          "question": "Artificial waterway nationalized by Nasser, leading to British and French intervention?",
          "answer": "Suez canal"
        },
        {
          "question": "Dam funded by the USSR that eventually created Lake Nasser",
          "answer": "Aswan Dam"
        },
        {
          "question": "Military clique of high ranking members which Nasser was a member?",
          "answer": "Free Officers Movement"
        },
        {
          "question": "Short-lived political Union between Syria and Nasser’s nation?",
          "answer": "United Arab Republic"
        },
        {
          "question": "Nation on the Arabian Peninsula whose Northern half Nasser invaded in its 1962-70 civil war?",
          "answer": "North Yemen"
        },
        {
          "question": "The King whom Nasser overthrew to begin his reign?",
          "answer": "King Farouk NHBB B 2014-2015"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Oil!",
      "prompt": "In the history of oil, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "founder of the Standard Oil Company.",
          "answer": "John Davidson Rockefeller"
        },
        {
          "question": "body of water where the Deepwater Horizon exploded in 2010.",
          "answer": "Gulf of Mexico"
        },
        {
          "question": "pipeline whose proposed Canada-to-Nebraska expasion was rejected by President Obama in 2015.",
          "answer": [
            "Keystone",
            "Keystone XL"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "oil tanker that crashed into Prince William Sound in 1989.",
          "answer": "Exxon Valdez"
        },
        {
          "question": "muckraker who wrote The History of the Standard Oil Company for McClure’s.",
          "answer": "Ida Minerva Tarbell"
        },
        {
          "question": "Wyoming oil field leased to Harry Sinclair by Albert Fall in 1922.",
          "answer": "Teapot Dome"
        },
        {
          "question": "concept, coined by M. King Hubbert, that oil will eventually cease to be economically viable, leading to a stark decline in oil production.",
          "answer": "peak oil"
        },
        {
          "question": "oil well drilled near Titusville, Pennsylvania in 1859, which triggered a boom in commercial oil drilling.",
          "answer": "Drake Well"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The European Union",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "country led from Ankara that has long tried to join the EU.",
          "answer": "Republic of Turkey"
        },
        {
          "question": "2009 treaty, named for the capital of Portugal, that overhauled the EU.",
          "answer": "Treaty of Lisbon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Balkan country with capital Zagreb that joined in 2013.",
          "answer": "Croatia"
        },
        {
          "question": "award won by the EU in 2012 for their efforts in representing human rights.",
          "answer": "Nobel Peace Prize"
        },
        {
          "question": "two commodities pooled in a common market by a predecessor to the EU.",
          "answer": [
            "coal and steel",
            "European Coal and Steel Community"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "treaty that established the European Union in 1993.",
          "answer": "Treaty of Maastricht"
        },
        {
          "question": "German co-architect of that treaty, who led the Christian Democrats and served as Chancellor of re-unified Germany.",
          "answer": "Helmut Kohl"
        },
        {
          "question": "area, named for a Luxembourg town, in which EU citizens can travel between other member states without a passport.",
          "answer": "Schengen Area"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The British Labour Party",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Legislative body, divided into the Houses of Commons and Lords, in which Labour has 231 members.",
          "answer": "Parliament of the United Kingdom"
        },
        {
          "question": "Side of the political spectrum to which Labour belongs. The term originated with the Jacobins and refers to more liberal policies.",
          "answer": "the political left"
        },
        {
          "question": "Organizations that allowed workers to collectively bargain, an early source of Labour political support.",
          "answer": [
            "trade unions",
            "labor unions"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Current leader of the Labour Party, an outspoken socialist who succeded Ed Miliband.",
          "answer": "Jeremy Corbyn"
        },
        {
          "question": "Moderate leader of the “New Labour” movement who was Prime Minister from 1997 to 2007.",
          "answer": "Tony Blair"
        },
        {
          "question": "Third party that joined with Labour to form several governments; its modern form entered a coalition with the Conservatives under Nick Clegg.",
          "answer": [
            "Liberal Party or the Liberal Democrats",
            "LibDems"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Labour Prime Minister who succeeded Churchill and introduced the National Health Service.",
          "answer": "Clement Attlee"
        },
        {
          "question": "First Labour Prime Minister, negatively affected by the Zinoviev letter.",
          "answer": "Ramsay MacDonald"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Supreme Court Justices",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Current Chief Justice.",
          "answer": "John Roberts"
        },
        {
          "question": "First Chief Justice.",
          "answer": "John Jay"
        },
        {
          "question": "First Latina justice, appointed by Barack Obama in 2009.",
          "answer": "Sonia Sotomayor"
        },
        {
          "question": "First female justice, appointed by Ronald Reagan.",
          "answer": "Sandra Day O’Connor"
        },
        {
          "question": "First African-American justice, appointed in 1967.",
          "answer": "Thurgood Marshall"
        },
        {
          "question": "First Jewish justice, appointed in 1916.",
          "answer": "Louis Brandeis"
        },
        {
          "question": "Only Justice to dissent in Plessy v. Ferguson.",
          "answer": "John Marshall Harlan I"
        },
        {
          "question": "Man who resigned as Associate Justice to run for President in 1916; he lost.",
          "answer": "Charles Evans Hughes"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Hurricanes",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "2005 hurricane that killed over 1,800 people and devastated New Orleans.",
          "answer": "Hurricane Katrina"
        },
        {
          "question": "U.S. territory where thousands were killed by Hurricane Maria in 2017.",
          "answer": "Puerto Rico"
        },
        {
          "question": "Agency of the Department of Homeland Security responsible for responding to hurricanes and other disasters.",
          "answer": "FEMA or Federal Emergency Management Agency"
        },
        {
          "question": "Politician whose failure leading that agency in 2005 led President Bush to tell him “you’re doing a heck of a job.”",
          "answer": [
            "Michael Brown",
            "“Brownie, you’re doing a heck of a job”"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Texas port city destroyed in 1900 by the deadliest hurricane in US history.",
          "answer": "Galveston"
        },
        {
          "question": "Atlantic hurricane that caused the closure of Atlantic City in 2012.",
          "answer": "Hurricane Sandy"
        },
        {
          "question": "Pair of civil engineers who, in 1971, developed a scale for classifying hurricanes.",
          "answer": "Herbert Saffir and William Simpson"
        },
        {
          "question": "Holiday on which a record setting hurricane struck Florida in 1935.",
          "answer": "1935 Labor Day hurricane"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The FBI",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "City where FBI headquarters is located on Pennsylvania Avenue, just east of the White House.",
          "answer": [
            "Washington, DC",
            "District of Columbia"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Cabinet-level department that oversees the FBI.",
          "answer": "Department of Justice"
        },
        {
          "question": "FBI director from 1924 to 1972 and namesake of their headquarters.",
          "answer": "John Edgar Hoover"
        },
        {
          "question": "Illegal good smuggled by “bootleggers,” early targets of the FBI.",
          "answer": [
            "alcohol",
            "equivalent answers",
            "any specific type"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "FBI director from 2001 to 2013 who served as Special Counsel investigating Russian interference in the 2016 election.",
          "answer": "Robert Mueller"
        },
        {
          "question": "Questionably legal program that infiltrated domestic political groups from 1956 to 1971 and tapped Martin Luther King’s phones.",
          "answer": [
            "COINTELPRO",
            "Counter Intelligence Program"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "FBI Associate Director who acted as “Deep Throat,” a source in the Watergate scandal.",
          "answer": "W. Mark Felt"
        },
        {
          "question": "Executive secretary who assisted in the destruction of thousands of “personal” files after the 1972 death of the FBI director.",
          "answer": "Helen Gandy"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Latin American Leaders",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Country where Alberto Fujimori was imprisoned in Lima after fleeing Japan.",
          "answer": "Peru"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country where the PRI’s Enrique Pen˜a Nieto was succeeded by Andr´es Manuel L´opez Obrador in 2018.",
          "answer": "Mexico"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country where Dilma Rousseff was impeached in 2016.",
          "answer": "Brazil"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country where Manuel Noriega was besieged by rock music in the Vatican embassy.",
          "answer": "Panama"
        },
        {
          "question": "President of Venezuela who called George W. Bush “the devil” at the UN in 2006.",
          "answer": "Hugo Chavez"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ruler who became President of Haiti after the death of his similarly brutal father in 1971.",
          "answer": [
            "Jean-Claude Duvalier",
            "Baby Doc"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "2016 Nobel Prize winner for negotiating a peace referendum with FARC.",
          "answer": "Juan Manuel Santos"
        },
        {
          "question": "Colorado leader who earned the nickname “Colonel Trunk” after being smuggled to safety in the back of a car in 1948.",
          "answer": "Alfredo Stroessner"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Regarding the administration of Bill Clinton, name the...",
      "prompt": "Name the regarding the administration of bill clinton, name the......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Prosperous decade during which the majority of Clinton's presidency occurred.",
          "answer": "1990s"
        },
        {
          "question": "White House intern subjected to a sex scandal along with the sitting President.",
          "answer": "Monica Lewinsky or Monica Samille Lewinsky"
        },
        {
          "question": "Supreme Court Justice, nicknamed RBG, who was nominated to be the second woman to serve on the court.",
          "answer": "Ruth Bader Ginsburg"
        },
        {
          "question": "Agreement signed by the Clinton administration, which was succeeded by Donald Trump’s USMCA.",
          "answer": [
            "NAFTA",
            "North American Free Trade Agreement"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Corrupt real estate venture which was investigated during the Clinton years.",
          "answer": [
            "Whitewater Development Corporation",
            "Whitewater Scandal/Controversy"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Female Attorney General who ordered the assault on the Waco compound.",
          "answer": "Janet Reno or Janet Wood Reno"
        },
        {
          "question": "Agreement named for an Ohio city which ended the Bosnian War.",
          "answer": "Dayton Accords"
        },
        {
          "question": "Law which was repealed, requiring commercial banks and investment banks to be separate.",
          "answer": "Glass-Steagall Act 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 3"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Connecticut History",
      "prompt": "Concerning Connecticut, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Capital city which names a failed treaty with the Dutch.",
          "answer": "Hartford"
        },
        {
          "question": "U.S. president born there who was in office during Operation Iraqi Freedom.",
          "answer": [
            "George Walker Bush",
            "Bush 43",
            "Bush the Younger"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Midwestern state in which Connecticut had its \"Western Reserve.\"",
          "answer": "Ohio"
        },
        {
          "question": "Senator and signer of the Constitution who proposed the Connecticut Compromise.",
          "answer": "Roger Sherman"
        },
        {
          "question": "Slave ship towed into its waters after a revolt led by Joseph Cinqué [[sin-KEH]].",
          "answer": "La Amistad"
        },
        {
          "question": "Democratic senator, later an independent, whom Al Gore chose as his running mate in 2000.",
          "answer": "Joe Lieberman or Joseph Isadore Lieberman"
        },
        {
          "question": "Governor elected in 1975, the first woman in the U.S. elected in her own right.",
          "answer": [
            "Ella T. Grasso or Ella Rosa Giovianna Oliva Grasso",
            "Ella Tambussi"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Baptist association which received a Thomas Jefferson letter mentioning \"separation between Church and State.\"",
          "answer": "Danbury Baptist Association or Danbury Baptists 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 9"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Hungary",
      "prompt": "Concerning Hungary, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Capital which takes its name from the combination of two Medieval cities.",
          "answer": "Budapest"
        },
        {
          "question": "Neighbor once led by the Habsburgs, which formed a dual monarchy in 1867.",
          "answer": [
            "Austria",
            "Osterreich"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Head of the Conservative Fidesz [[FEE-dess]] Party, who became prime minister in 2010.",
          "answer": "Viktor Orbán or Viktor Mihály Orbán"
        },
        {
          "question": "Olympic aquatic sport whose 1956 semifinals match turned bloody due to tensions with the USSR.",
          "answer": "Water polo"
        },
        {
          "question": "Saint who was crowned first King of Hungary in the year 1000.",
          "answer": [
            "Stephen I",
            "Szent István király",
            "or Štefan Veľký"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Admiral and reluctant Nazi collaborator who was overthrown and replaced by the Fascist Arrow Cross Party.",
          "answer": [
            "Miklós Horthy ] or Nicholas Horthy",
            "or Miklós Horthy de Nagybánya"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Founder of Hungary who settled the Magyar [[MAH-gyar]] tribes in the Carpathian Basin.",
          "answer": "Árpád"
        },
        {
          "question": "Mixed form of communism practiced in Hungary by János Kádár [[YAH-nohsh KAH- dahr]].",
          "answer": "\"Goulash Communism\""
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Protestors in this country in 2014 often wore the number forty-three painted on their faces, a reminder of the September 2014 abduction of forty-three (20 pts)",
        "students at a teachers' college here. Protests targeted this country's president, who represents the (10 pts)",
        "PRI and defeated the incumbent PAN in the 2012 election. For 10 points, name this country where protestors demanded the resignation of Enrique Peña Nieto (en-REE-kay PEN-yah nee-EY-toe)."
      ],
      "answer": "Mexico"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This state’s loss at the first Battle of Himera led to the downfall of its Magonid dynasty. The Fabian strategy was developed to fight the armies of this city, which won battles at (20 pts)",
        "Trebia and Lake Trasimene after one of its commanders crossed the (10 pts)",
        "Alps. Cato the Elder famously ended his speeches by declaring that this city “must be destroyed”, or “delenda est”. For 10 points, name this city-state whose armies, led by Hamilcar and Hannibal Barca, fought Rome in the Punic Wars."
      ],
      "answer": "Carthage NHBB B 2014-2015"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Isabelle Falque-Pierrotin (FALK pee-ROH-tah), a French government official, has launched a campaign for global implementation of this legal privilege, which was first implemented in May 2014 after (20 pts)",
        "Mario Costeja (coh-STAY-hah) González's case was upheld by the (10 pts)",
        "European Court of Justice. For 10 points, name this right, unsuccessfully contested by Google, which allows an individual to have his or her name removed from search engine indexing."
      ],
      "answer": "\"right to be forgotten\""
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) An all-night ritual at Bois [BWAH] Caiman preceded this uprising, whose leader turned on each other in the War of the Knives. The Code Noir oppressed the eventual victors of this war, such as (20 pts)",
        "Jean-Jacques Dessalines. Napoleonic troops in this conflict died of dysentery trying to save the largest coffee and (10 pts)",
        "sugar plantations in the Western hemisphere. For 10 points, name this slave revolt that ended Saint-Domingue, which Toussaint L'Ouverture led on the western side of Hispaniola."
      ],
      "answer": "Haitian Revolution NHBB B 2014-2015"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) An object aboard this vessel includes Blind Willie Johnson's recording of \"Dark Was the Night, Cold Was the Ground\" and the first Brandenburg Concerto, as well as greetings in fifty-five languages. This vessel, which holds a (20 pts)",
        "\"golden record\" compiled by Carl Sagan, was launched in 1977 and left the (10 pts)",
        "solar system in 2013. For 10 points, name this probe which is currently the farthest manmade object from Earth."
      ],
      "answer": "Voyager 1"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In the 1920s, this party divided into \"black and tan\" and \"lily white\" factions in a dispute over allowing African-American support. A dissident faction of this party briefly broke away in 1870 under Carl Schurz and cross-nominated (20 pts)",
        "Horace Greeley for President in 1872; that party appended the word (10 pts)",
        "\"liberal\" to this party's name. For 10 points, name this party that engineered Reconstruction, and won the Presidency under Abraham Lincoln."
      ],
      "answer": "Republican Party NHBB B 2014-2015"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In mid-2014, popular examples of this kind of product included the Moto 360 and Pebble\nSteel. Samsung launched several of these products under the (20 pts) ",
        "\"Gear\" line, and these\nproducts are named for a Sony line that integrates with (10 pts) ",
        "Android operating systems. For\n10 points, Apple caused a stir by announcing the launch of their version of what kind of wearable\ntechnology product, which is often used for fitness monitoring or portable media capabilities?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "smart watches"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man was embarrassed by the 2002 release of Nixon White House tapes in which he\naccused Jews of belonging to the \"synagogue of Satan.\" This man, who has taken credit for\nconvincing Dwight Eisenhower to (20 pts) ",
        "desegregate schools in Arkansas, became famous for\nhis Festival of Hope and (10 pts) ",
        "ecumenical revivals, which close with the hymn \"Just As I Am.\"\nFor 10 points, name this frequent Presidential advisor and most successful evangelist in\nAmerican history."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Billy Graham",
        "Graham"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This country's central bank adopted a policy of “forward guidance” for future interest\nrates after the 2008 financial crisis. It froze Icelandic bank assets in 2008 after Iceland\nrefused to guarantee its banks' debts to creditors in this country. The Chancellor of the (20 pts) ",
        "Exchequer proposed large spending cuts in 2010 as part of the austerity program of its\nformer prime minister, (10 pts) ",
        "David Cameron. For 10 points, name this country whose\ngovernment nationalized the Royal Bank of Scotland."
      ],
      "answer": "United Kingdom"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The winner of this sporting event is awarded the Harley J. Earl Trophy, and Sterling Marlin is the most recent back-to-back winner, doing so in 1994 and 1995. Dale (20 pts)",
        "Jarrett is the most recent to win it from the pole. Its 2014 winner was Dale (10 pts)",
        "Earnhardt Jr., who drove the #21 Chevrolet to Victory Lane. For 10 points, name this automobile race, the first event in NASCAR's annual Sprint Cup series, and which takes place at a namesake track in Northern Florida."
      ],
      "answer": "Daytona 500"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Critic Fred Hobson mused that this technology would have made writing the novels of William Faulkner impossible. This technology was named by Stuart Cramer after early models by John Gorrie and Edward Elis were perfected in 1902 in Buffalo, by Willis (20 pts)",
        "Carrier. These devices allowed for the post-war economic and population boom in the (10 pts)",
        "South. For 10 points, name these devices which use freon or other liquids to dehumidify and cool buildings."
      ],
      "answer": "air conditioners NHBB B 2014-2015"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this country, forty-one inmates at the David Viloria prison died in November 2014; the government says the inmates overdosed on medications after breaking into an infirmary, but human rights monitors blame intentional poisoning. This country also announced (20 pts)",
        "wage cuts following a drop in the price of (10 pts)",
        "oil, which comprises nearly all of its exports. For 10 points, name this South American country led by Nicholas Maduro, who succeeded Hugo Chavez."
      ],
      "answer": "Venezuela"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This procedure was first worked out using methane collected from the Baltimore sewers as a sample. James Arnold acquired samples from the tomb of Zoser to further refine this procedure, for which (20 pts)",
        "Willard Libby won a Nobel Prize. This procedure relies on the fact that isotope (10 pts)",
        "14 of its namesake element decays at a known rate over time. For 10 points, identify this procedure which determines the age of organic matter chemically."
      ],
      "answer": "radiocarbon dating NHBB B 2014-2015"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) King Charles XII of Sweden planned to adopt this system over a period of forty years from 1700 to 1740, but gave up in 1711. The adoption of this system in England in 1750 apocryphally caused rioters to chant “Give us our (20 pts)",
        "eleven days.” The major change of this system over its predecessor is its treatment of (10 pts)",
        "years divisible by 400. For 10 points, name this calendar system which replaced the Julian Calendar and which is named for the Pope who introduced it in 1582."
      ],
      "answer": "Gregorian calendar NHBB B 2014-2015"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Kurt Shmoke's 2013 article on this President's little-known civil rights record discussed his advocacy of increasing funding for the medical college at Howard University. This man, who repeatedly vetoed the McNary-Haugen farm relief bill, agreed to the (20 pts)",
        "Kellogg- Briand Pact outlawing war. He came to prominence as the governor of (10 pts)",
        "Massachussetts, where he broke the Boston police strike. For 10 points, name this taciturn successor of Warren Harding."
      ],
      "answer": "Calvin Coolidge"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 2008, 300,000 people in this country were injured when melamine was added to food, particularly infant formula. In 2010, the US Embassy in this country’s capital tweeted that its AQI reached 700, briefly calling it “crazy bad.” The 2002-03 (20 pts)",
        "SARS outbreak began in this country, where almost 70,000 people were killed by the 2008 (10 pts)",
        "Sichaun earthquake. For ten points, name this country where factories were shut down to clear the air prior to the 2008 Summer Olympics in Beijing."
      ],
      "answer": "People’s Republic of China"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Victor Espinoza and Bob Baffert’s work with this athlete resulted in a runner-up finish at Saratoga and nine victories. Sports Illustrated was criticized for naming (20 pts)",
        "Serena Williams its 2015 Sportsman of the Year over this athlete, who completed a Grand Slam with his (10 pts)",
        "Breeders’ Cup victory. For ten points, name this horse who won the Belmont, Preakness, and Kentucky Derby to complete horse racing’s first Triple Crown since 1978."
      ],
      "answer": "American Pharoah"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This specific concept was described as the “heart of a heartless world” by one thinker. “They keep you doped with” this concept, “sex, and TV” according to John Lennon’s “Working Class Hero.” In 2008, (20 pts)",
        "Barack Obama explained that “it’s not surprising” that unemployed small-town people “get bitter” and “cling to (10 pts)",
        "guns or” this concept. For ten points, name this concept, described by Karl Marx as the “opium of the people,” whose varieties include Christianity."
      ],
      "answer": "religion"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Sherron Watkins blew the whistle on this company, which caused blackouts in California in 2000 with its manipulative speculating. The Sarbanes-Oxley Act was passed in the wake of this company’s end, after which the (20 pts)",
        "Arthur Andersen accounting firm was discredited and Jeff Skilling and (10 pts)",
        "Ken Lay were convicted of fraud. For ten points, name this energy company based in Houston, Texas, which suffered the largest Chapter 11 bankruptcy in U.S. history in 2001."
      ],
      "answer": "Enron Corporation"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this state in 2012, Marissa Alexander fired a “warning shot” at her estranged husband. An unarmed resident of this state’s city of Sanford was shot by George (20 pts)",
        "Zimmerman; in the ensuing trial, the defense did not invoke this state’s 2005 “Stand Your Ground” law, as Zimmerman instead claimed self-defense against (10 pts)",
        "Trayvon Martin. For ten points, name this state where the Stand Your Ground law was expanded in 2014 by Governor Rick Scott."
      ],
      "answer": "Florida"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The 2010 U.S. Olympic hockey team wore dog tags honoring this action done by Brendan Burke. The Nets’ number 98 jersey became a top-seller after its wearer performed this action, and another man did it after leaving Leeds United for the (20 pts)",
        "L.A. Galaxy in May 2013. A former SEC Defensive Player of the Year for the University of Missouri dropped to the seventh round of the 2014 (10 pts)",
        "NFL draft after performing this action. For ten points, name this action performed by Jason Collins, Robbie Rogers, and Michael Sam when they publicized their sexuality."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "coming out",
        "equivalents like telling people that they are gay"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A Supreme Court case arising from this U.S. state debated the validity of a December 12th “safe harbor” deadline. Republicans operatives were flown into this state to cause the Brooks Brothers Riot. (20 pts)",
        "Katherine Harris served as its Secretary of State during an election marked by awkward “butterfly (10 pts)",
        "ballots,” which may have caused this state’s voters to mark their ballots for Pat Buchanan instead of Al Gore. For ten points, name this state whose 25 electoral votes clinched the 2000 Presidential election for George W. Bush, the brother of its Governor, Jeb."
      ],
      "answer": "Florida"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A senator from this state was killed in a plane crash eleven days before the 2002 election, after which Norm Coleman became the most recent Republican to win a Senate seat from this state. Paul Wellstone served in this state’s (20 pts)",
        "Democratic-Farmer-Labor party, which replaced him on the 2002 ballot with Walter Mondale. Mark Dayton is the current governor of, and (10 pts)",
        "Amy Klobuchar and Al Franken are the current senators from, for ten points, what U.S. state where Coleman had served as mayor of St. Paul?"
      ],
      "answer": "Minnesota"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) At a State of the Union speech, Barack Obama claimed that this case “reversed a century of law.” This case upheld the legality of 60 day buffers and partially overturned a 2002 Supreme Court case involving Mitch (20 pts)",
        "McConnell. This case arose after the plaintiffs were prevented from advertising for Hillary: The Movie by the McCain-Feingold Act. First Amendment protections on free (10 pts)",
        "speech were cited in, for ten points, what 2010 Supreme Court case that struck down certain campaign financing laws?"
      ],
      "answer": "Citizens United vs. Federal Election Commission or FEC"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 1972, dissident poet Pedro Luis Boitel died in one of these events in Cuba. In 1980, one of these events was briefly led by Brendan Hughes; when its demands weren’t met, this event was re-started, and (20 pts)",
        "Provisional IRA member Bobby Sands was the first to die. The World Medical Association declares that attempts to forcefully end these events are considered torture, as has been done at (10 pts)",
        "Guantanamo Bay using IV bags. For ten points, name this event in which a protester refuses nourishment. ANSWER:hunger strike(acceptdescriptions;promptongeneraltermslike“(political)protest;”prompt on descriptions of suicide (attempts)) (5) In 2007, six people were extradited from this country to Bulgaria, where President Georgi Parvanov pardoned them for allegedly infecting 400 children in this country with HIV. From 2014 to 2016, this country’s port city of Derna was under the control of ISIS. This country’s (+) Council of Deputies runs a government that rivals an internationally- recognized government in Tobruk. Christopher (*) Stevens, a former ambassador to this country, was killed in a 2012 attack in Benghazi. For ten points, name this African country led until 2011 by Muammar Gaddafi."
      ],
      "answer": "Libya"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this country, the Khalq and Parcham factions of the People’s Democratic Party split in the lead-up to the PDP’s revolt against Mohammed Daoud Khan; Khan was then assassinated by Khalqist military forces, sparking the Saur Revolution in (20 pts)",
        "1978. In 1996, Ahmad Shah Massoud co-founded the Northern Alliance to oppose a majority-Pashtun military government; that alliance eventually dissolved after Hamid Karzai became its president, supported by the U.S. after its (10 pts)",
        "2001 invasion. For ten points, name this country, once ruled by the Taliban from its capital of Kabul."
      ],
      "answer": "Islamic Republic of Afghanistan"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this election year, after Paul Tsongas won the New Hampshire primary, the second-place finisher declared himself “the Comeback Kid” and went on to win his party’s nomination. Another candidate in this year briefly (20 pts)",
        "dropped out of the race, apparently because Republicans had tried to ruin his daughter’s wedding; that candidate warned against the “giant sucking sound” of jobs going south to Mexico should his independent candidacy lose and (10 pts)",
        "NAFTA be passed. Ross Perot’s first presidential campaign took third in, for ten points, what election year in which Bill Clinton defeated incumbent George H. W. Bush?"
      ],
      "answer": "Presidential election of 1992"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This leader returned to power four years after a leaked speech revealed that the MSZP, his country’s Socialist Party, lied “morning, at noon, and at night” about its ability to govern. In 2014, this leader proposed “illberal democracy” and a governing style more like (20 pts)",
        "Turkey or Russia. 44% voter turnout stymied this Fidesz Party leader’s 2016 referendum opposing EU migrant quotas, a year after this leader built a barbed wire fence on his country’s southern border with (10 pts)",
        "Serbia. For ten points, name this current Prime Minister of Hungary."
      ],
      "answer": "Viktor Orban"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This artist sang “It don’t take too much high IQ’s to see what you’re doing to me” in her appearance in the original Blues Brothers film. This singer, who performed “My Country, ‘Tis of Thee” at the (20 pts)",
        "2009 inauguration of President Obama, received the Presidential Medal of Freedom in 2005 for a career that included 11 Grammys for Best Female (10 pts)",
        "R&B Vocal Performance. For ten points, name this “Queen of Soul” whose hits include “Think,” “Chain of Fools,” and “Respect.”"
      ],
      "answer": "Aretha Franklin"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 2015, members of this group noted “It. Just. Isn’t. That. Good.” in their two-star review of In the Aeroplane Over the Sea by Neutral Milk Hotel. That review was labeled “Disgusting” by a website that later praised a State Department effort to counter this group: a world map with the US (20 pts)",
        "shrunk to be too small for this group to find. In real life, a member of this group used the caption “We respawn in Jannah” in an (10 pts)",
        "Instagram post referencing Call of Duty, one of its numerous recruitment attempts over social media. Clickhole.com frequently lampoons, for ten points, what terrorist group that lost control of Mosul in July 2017?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "ISIS or Islamic State of Iraq and Syria",
        "or ISIL",
        "or Islamic State of Iraq and the Levant",
        "or Daesh",
        "descriptions of Clickhole.com’s version of ISIS"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In October 2016, an attack against these people in Maungdaw was carried out by Harakah al-Yaqin insurgents. A government began resettling this group to the manmade island of Thengar Char in January 2017, much to the dismay of (20 pts)",
        "human rights groups. The United Nations said it was “very likely” that crimes against humanity were taking place against these people, who primarily live in (10 pts)",
        "Rakhine State, north of the Bay of Bengal. Aung San Suu Kyi [chee] has been heavily criticized for her silence on the persecution of, for ten points, what Muslim ethnic group that primarily lives in Burma?"
      ],
      "answer": "Rohingya people"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this election year, the losing ticket’s vice presidential nominee developed the recurring theme of the “Two Americas;” that politician then lost his position as Senator from North Carolina. After this election year’s (20 pts)",
        "Iowa caucuses, the third-place finisher shouted “Yeah!” at the end of his rallying speech; that shriek by Howard Dean is largely thought to have doomed his campaign. (10 pts)",
        "Veterans used “swiftboating” to attack the Democratic nominee in this year. For ten points, name this year in which John Edwards and John Kerry lost to the re-election campaign of George W. Bush."
      ],
      "answer": "U.S. Presidential Election of 2004"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) These events were governed by a two-thirds rule that led to a bitter conflict between the Wet and Dry factions in 1924. The McGovern-Fraser Commission was created to solve the problems that arose at one of these events that was marred by (20 pts)",
        "Robert Kennedy’s assassination three months earlier. At the 2016 version of this event, Khizr Khan, a Gold Star parent, criticized (10 pts)",
        "Donald Trump’s campaign promises. For ten points, name this quadrennial event at which politicians like Barack Obama and Hillary Clinton have been nominated to run for President by their party."
      ],
      "answer": "Democratic National Conventions or DNCs"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Vice Admiral William McRaven organized this event, which was planned for the night of the White House Correspondents Dinner. In the aftermath of this event, the perpetrators consulted the (20 pts)",
        "Saudi Arabian government while onboard the USS Carl Vinson before burying a corpse in the North Arabian (10 pts)",
        "Sea. A courier named Abu Ahmed al-Kuwaiti was tracked to discover the location of this event’s target, who was codenamed “Geronimo.” For ten points, name this May 2, 2011 event in which members of SEAL Team Six killed the leader of Al-Qaeda."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "assassination or killing, shooting, etc. of Osama bin Laden",
        "Operation Neptune Spear"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One of these things inspired and names the second and most famous symphonic poem in Bedrich Smetana’s collection Ma vlast, known as “The Moldau” or “Vltava.” The spacecraft docking scene in (20 pts)",
        "2001: A Space Odyssey was set to a piece of music named for one of these things. Handel’s Water Music was commissioned to be played while King George II (10 pts)",
        "traveled along one of these features. For ten points, name this type of geographic feature that inspired Johann Strauss’ waltz “On the Beautiful Blue Danube.”"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "rivers",
        "Danube River after “spacecraft” is read",
        "Thames River after “Handel” is read"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 2006 in this country, police used force to bar flower vendors from a marketplace, sparking a protest in which students identified themselves by university IDs, the “I am 132” movement. A 2012 (20 pts)",
        "election in this country sparked protests when media bias allegedly contributed to the defeat of Josefina Mota, head of the PAN [spell it]. The (10 pts)",
        "PRI [spell it] currently leads, for ten points, what country where Enrique Pena Nieto was succeeded in 2018 by Andres Manuel Lopez Obrador?"
      ],
      "answer": "Mexico"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A 1993 attack on this organization’s headquarters was carried out by Pakistani terrorist Mir Qazi. In a 2003 scandal, Robert Novak revealed that Valerie Plame worked for this organization. Following revelations of his (20 pts)",
        "affair with Paula Broadwell, David Petraeus stepped down as head of this organization, which helped plan an assassination in (10 pts)",
        "Abbottabad, Pakistan carried out by Seal Team Six. The assassination of Osama bin Laden was masterminded by, for ten points, what American agency that engages in covert action overseas?"
      ],
      "answer": "Central Intelligence Agency"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This event inspired most of the album The Rising by Bruce Springsteen, including its song “My City of Ruins.” Clear Channel Communications released a memo suggesting that “Imagine” by John Lennon, every song by Rage Against the Machine, and over 100 other songs (20 pts)",
        "not be played on the radio in the wake of this event. Paul McCartney’s single “Freedom” was written after he witnessed this event from the (10 pts)",
        "tarmac of JFK airport in Queens. For ten points, name this terrorist attack that was memorialized by a benefit concert in New York in October 2001."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "September 11th, 2001 attacks",
        "9/11 attacks",
        "2001 World Trade Center attacks and any other specific aspect of the 9/11 attacks"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Many hypotheses about this event were strengthened by a 2016 project to drill into the only extant peak ring on Earth; the drilling found pink granite and shocked quartz. The (20 pts)",
        "Alvarez family studied this event and posed the most prominent hypothesis about its origins. This event is often known as the “K-T event” for the symbols for the eras of geologic time it separates. A (10 pts)",
        "meteor impact at what is now the Yucatan Peninsula probably caused, for ten points, what event that, roughly 66 million years ago, wiped out nearly all large reptiles on Earth?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Cretaceous-Tertiary extinction event extinction event before “K-T” is mentioned",
        "descriptions of “the end of the dinosaurs”"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This leader introduced the Restoration of Sovereignty Day in 2013, marking the 61st anniversary of the Americans leaving his country. People have speculated that this leader’s wife, Akie, pretended to not know English to avoid (20 pts)",
        "speaking to Donald Trump at a G-20 summit. During this leader’s tenure, his government faced both nationalistic (10 pts)",
        "anti-Korean riots and the Fukushima nuclear disaster. For ten points, name this Prime Minister of Japan who has led since 2012."
      ],
      "answer": "Shinzo Abe"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One man with this surname was the longest-serving governor of New York and served as Vice President under both Thomas Jefferson and James Madison. Another man with this surname sponsored the construction of the (20 pts)",
        "Erie Canal, which was nicknamed his “ditch.” In addition to George and DeWitt, another man with this surname signed (10 pts)",
        "NAFTA into law and served as the governor of Arkansas; that man came under fire for his affair with the White House intern Monica Lewinsky. For ten points, give this surname shared by politicians Bill and Hillary."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Clinton",
        "George Clinton, DeWitt Clinton, Bill Clinton, William Jefferson Clinton III, and/or Hillary Clinton"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Composer Karlheinz Stockhausen controversially described this event as “the biggest work of art there has ever been.” A “memory space” composed after this event opens with the repeating word (20 pts)",
        "“missing” and includes a tape recording of a list of its victims; that piece is John Adams’ On the Transmigration of Souls. The musical (10 pts)",
        "Come From Away depicts Operation Yellow Ribbon in the Newfoundland town of Gander, where dozens of planes were diverted during, for ten points, what terrorist attack in which nearly 3,000 people were killed in 2001?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "September 11th attacks",
        "9/11",
        "descriptions of any individual attack on 9/11/2001, but"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) These people, who were the main inhabitants of the Mayu Frontier District, were targeted in Operation King Dragon. These people were armed by the British “V-Force” and fought against pro-Japanese Red Karens. Many of these people have sought asylum at (20 pts)",
        "Cox’s Bazar after a series of 2012 riots led to their mass persecution. These inhabitants of (10 pts)",
        "Rakhine State have been subject to attacks by Theravada Buddhists in their home country. For ten points, name this Muslim ethnic group whose members have sought asylum in Bangladesh after fleeing Burma."
      ],
      "answer": "Rohingya people"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This state was the site of the SS Grandcamp disaster, in which nearly 600 people died after over 4 million pounds of ammonium nitrate exploded in 1947. In April 2013, this state’s town of West was (20 pts)",
        "rocked by another ammonium nitrate explosion. A 2019 chemical plant explosion caused evacuations in this state’s Beaumont-Port Arthur metropolitan area, on the western shores of the (10 pts)",
        "Sabine Lake near the Gulf of Mexico. For ten points, name this state where the booming petrochemical industry fueled the growth of cities like Houston."
      ],
      "answer": "Texas"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A leader of this country claimed that its own citizens would “eat grass,” if necessary, to develop its own nuclear arsenal if a rival nation did so. Baitullah Mehsud was accused of ordering the 2007 assassination of this country’s former prime minister, (20 pts)",
        "Benazir Bhutto. In 1940, Muhammad Ali Jinnah worked to pass the Lahore Resolution, demanding that the UK grant independence to this nation, separate from its (10 pts)",
        "majority-Hindu neighbor. For ten points, name this primarily Muslim country created by the Partition of India."
      ],
      "answer": "Islamic Republic of Pakistan 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Round 1"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Aaron Schock, a congressman from this state, resigned after being accused of buying luxury items with government money. Mike Madigan, Speaker of the House in this state, faced a 2020 investigation over a bribery scandal and was urged to step down by Governor J. B. (20 pts)",
        "Pritzker. An FBI operation called Silver Shovel discovered that aldermen in this state’s (10 pts)",
        "Cook County were complicit in illegal activities. For ten points, name this state where George Ryan and Rod Blagojevich [[blah-GOY-eh-vitch]] once governed from Springfield."
      ],
      "answer": "Illinois"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One of the colors of this flag represents both the hue of the rhododendron flower and bravery, while the color of its border represents peace and harmony. An earlier version of this flag featured two human faces, but those faces were removed from its (20 pts)",
        "sun and moon in 1962. When constructed according to the process mandated in its country’s 2015 Constitution, this flag’s aspect ratio is an (10 pts)",
        "irrational number. For ten points, name this emblem of an Asian nation, the world’s only non- quadrilateral national standard."
      ],
      "answer": "Flag of Nepal"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Members of this ethnic group blew up the car of a prime minister nicknamed his country's \"first astronaut\" in Operation Ogre. Whalers of this ethnic group who spoke an Algonquian-based pidgin were massacred in 1615 in Iceland. Luis Carrero (20 pts)",
        "Blanco was killed by a terrorist group of this ethnic group called the ETA, which was falsely blamed for the 2004 Madrid train bombings. Francisco Franco attempted to suppress this ethnic group by carrying out the (10 pts)",
        "bombing of Guernica. For ten points, name this Spanish ethnic group, who speak a language isolate called Euskara."
      ],
      "answer": "Basques or Euskaldunak"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This battle's namesake campaign ended with the Battle of Forts Clinton and Montgomery. Redoubts at this battle were led by Lord Balcarres and Heinrich von Breymann. Timothy Murphy likely shot and killed Simon Fraser at this battle. The surrendered troops formed the (20 pts)",
        "Convention Army at this battle, which led to a Franco-American alliance. This battle included fights at Bemis (10 pts)",
        "Heights and Freeman's Farm. For ten points, name this 1777 battle at which Horatio Gates defeated John Burgoyne in upstate New York."
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Saratoga 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Round 2"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this year, a sitting US president visited Cuba for the first time in 95 years. Writers Elie Wiesel [[EE-lee vee-ZEL]] and Harper Lee died in this year as did hockey great Gordie Howe, whose June death occurred on a palindrome day. In January of this year, the World (20 pts)",
        "Health Organization reported that the Zika virus was spreading rapidly through the Americas. The World Series winner in this year broke the 108-year (10 pts)",
        "Chicago Cubs curse. For ten points, identify the year in which Barack Obama visited Cuba and endorsed Hillary Clinton for president."
      ],
      "answer": "2016"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A leader of this state issued the \"kvindefred\" ordinance and expanded the Brigittine Language. Henry IV's daughter, Philippa of Lancaster, married into this state. A founder of this state was called \"King Breechless\" and \"Semiramis of the North” and was succeeded by (20 pts)",
        "Bogislav. This state faced the Engelbrekt rebellion against its leader Eric of Pomerania. At the Treaty of Malmo, this transnational state lost (10 pts)",
        "Sweden, a result of Gustav Vasa's successful capture of Stockholm. Queen Margaret led, for ten points, what Scandinavian Union?"
      ],
      "answer": "Kalmar Union 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Round 4"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Daniel Williams and Glenn Foard helped identify this battle's location, which is contested by Peter Foss's \"Redemore\" theory. The blind historian Bernard André was so overwhelmed by this battle's importance that he left a blank page for it in his opus. The Duke of (20 pts)",
        "Norfolk may have died at this battle near the Dadlington windmill, and Richard Ratcliffe was killed at this battle at which the Stanleys joined the winners. Henry (10 pts)",
        "VII defeated Richard III in, for ten points, what closing battle of the Wars of the Roses?"
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Bosworth Field 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Round 4"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 2012, this man was charged with stealing timber from the company Kirovles. This founder of \"The People\" movement had to pay millions in fines in the Yves Rocher case. This founder of the Anti-Corruption Foundation lost in a 2013 election to Sergey (20 pts)",
        "Sobyanin. In an interview, this man called United Russia a \"party of crooks and thieves.” While on a flight to Tomsk, this man was (10 pts)",
        "poisoned with the Novichok nerve agent. For ten points, name this Russian anti-corruption activist described as the \"man Vladimir Putin fears most.\""
      ],
      "answer": "Alexei Navalny"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In the 1960s, this site was excavated by Yigael Yadin, who discovered 28 human remains and a number of bathhouses. Lucius Flavius Silva laid siege to this site and constructed a massive siege ramp completed in 73 CE. (20 pts)",
        "Josephus wrote of two speeches that a Sicari leader made at this site convincing his men to kill themselves. Herod the Great built two palaces for himself at this site, which was besieged following the First (10 pts)",
        "Jewish War. For ten points, name this fortress captured by the Roman army in the Judaean Desert, which overlooks the Dead Sea."
      ],
      "answer": "Masada 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Playoff Round 2"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This woman earned a PhD from Columbia’s Department of Public Law and Governance and became a professor at Georgetown in 1982. When introducing Hillary Clinton in 2016, this woman said, “There is a special place in hell for (20 pts)",
        "women who don’t help each other.” In 2012, this woman had a tense meeting with a group of activists from her homeland as a result of her role in the NATO bombing of Serbia. This native of (10 pts)",
        "Czechoslovakia was nominated to her highest post by President Bill Clinton. For ten points, name this woman, the first female Secretary of State."
      ],
      "answer": "Madeleine Albright 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Playoff Round 2"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This person was almost freed in the Carnation Plot, foiled by the incorruptibility of the guards. This person was jailed as Prisoner Number 280 in the Conciergerie. Once called the \"Widow Capet,” this woman's son was given (20 pts)",
        "to the cobbler Antoine Simon. Edme-Bonaventure Courtois found this person's will among Robespierre's papers. With her reputation damaged in the (10 pts)",
        "Affair of the Diamond Necklace, this woman was guillotined after her husband. This person likely never said, \"Let them eat cake.” For ten points, name this Queen of France, the wife of Louis XVI."
      ],
      "answer": "Marie Antoinette 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Playoff Round 3"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The statue Lifting of the Veil of Ignorance at this location depicts a formerly enslaved man being shown the proper path by its founder. This site's Moton Field served as training grounds for its namesake \"Airmen\" who (20 pts)",
        "fought in the Second World War. An unethical study named for this institution left syphilis untreated in four hundred Black male sharecroppers for forty years to study its effects. George Washington (10 pts)",
        "Carver studied at, for ten points, which Alabama university once led by Booker T. Washington?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Tuskegee Institute",
        "Tuskegee University 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 1"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Flights from this nation to Belarus were halted in November 2021 to stop Middle Eastern migrants from entering the EU. A 2016 coup attempt in this nation may have been manufactured by its president to purge the military of enemies. The (20 pts)",
        "Kurdish PKK party fought an asymmetrical war with this nation's government, which is led by Recep Tayyip Erdoğan [[EHR-doh-wahn]]. ISIS (10 pts)",
        "may have perpetrated the 2015 Ankara Bombings in, for ten points, what Anatolian nation?"
      ],
      "answer": "Republic of Turkey or Türkiye Cumhuriyeti 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 1"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) After the Pledge of the Tree, this diplomat guaranteed the procession of the first Umrah pilgrimage by negotiating the Treaty of Hudaybiyyah [[hoo-day-BEE- yah]]. A Pagan-Jewish confederation besieged this man's capital during the Battle of the (20 pts)",
        "Trench, some time after this man began a war with the Quraysh [[KOO-raysh]] tribe following the Battle of Badr. The capture of (10 pts)",
        "Mecca was accomplished by, for ten points, which general and Prophet of the Islamic faith?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Muhammad ibn Abdullah",
        "Mohammed 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 2"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This person's first purported miracle occurred when a locket containing their image supposedly rid Monica Besra of a malignant tumor. This figure faced controversy for her tacit support of her homeland's Hoxha [[HOH-shuh]] regime (20 pts)",
        "and Indira Gandhi's suspension of civil liberties during \"The Emergency.\" This woman of Albanian descent founded the Missionaries of Charity and served the slums of (10 pts)",
        "Kolkata. For ten points, name this Nobel Peace Prize winner and canonized nun of the 20th century."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Mother Teresa",
        "Mary Teresa Bojaxhiu",
        "Saint Teresa of Calcutta 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 3"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) J.A. Wayland gave this work early exposure by publishing it serially in his socialist paper, Appeal to Reason. This work, which aimed to unveil poor working conditions in Chicago, (20 pts)",
        "led to its author claiming \"[he] aimed at the public's heart and by accident [he] hit it in the stomach.\" The passage of the Pure (10 pts)",
        "Food and Drug Act was partially motivated by, for ten points, which muckraking exposé of the meatpacking industry written by Upton Sinclair?"
      ],
      "answer": "The Jungle 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 4"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this state, an indoor concert by hair metal band Great White led to a fire in West Warwick which killed one hundred attendees. In 2015, the governor of this state proposed a luxury tax on second homes which the media dubbed the \"Taylor Swift (20 pts)",
        "Tax\" due to her having beachfront property there. That governor of this state, Gina Raimondo, resigned to become Joe Biden's Secretary of Commerce. The words \"Providence (10 pts)",
        "Plantations\" were dropped from the name of, for ten points, which New England state?"
      ],
      "answer": "Rhode Island 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 6"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man was subpoenaed for his knowledge of Operation Red Dog, a neo-Nazi attempt to seize the island of Dominica in the early 1980s. This man is the oldest person to receive an electoral vote, which he received from Bill Greene in the 2016 election. This first chairman of the (20 pts)",
        "Citizens for a Sound Economy organized the early Tea Party protests in the 2000s. The (10 pts)",
        "father of Kentucky senator Rand is, for ten points, which Libertarian presidential candidate, a former representative from Texas?"
      ],
      "answer": "Ron Paul or Ron Ernest Paul"
    }
  ]
}